<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The royal flight, or, The conquest of Ireland a new farce.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57786</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2129</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23077</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12062815</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12062815</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53309</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57786)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53309)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 577:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The royal flight, or, The conquest of Ireland a new farce.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 57, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [2]-[3] at end.</note>
                  <note>Perhaps the second part of "The royal voyage, or The Irish expedition: a tragicomedy, acted in the years 1689 and 90", issued by the same publisher in 1690.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701 --  Drama.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53309:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53309:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Royal Flight: OR, THE CONQUEST OF IRELAND. A NEW FARCE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:53309:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53309:2"/>
            <head>The Perſons.</head>
            <list>
               <item>K. J.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. of</hi> Berwick.</item>
               <item>Tyrconnel.</item>
               <item>Powis.</item>
               <item>Herbert.</item>
               <item>Nugent.</item>
               <item>Lutterel.</item>
               <item>Talbot, <hi>Pretended Primate.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Arch Biſhop of</hi> Caſſels.</item>
               <item>Sarsfield.</item>
               <item>Hamilton.</item>
               <item>Mac-Guillicuddy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>D'</hi>Avaux,</item>
               <item>Lauzune.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>La</hi> Hoquette.</item>
               <item>Leri, <hi>Ld. Mayor of</hi> Dublin</item>
               <item>Hall, <hi>the Prieſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Prieſts <hi>and</hi> Jeſuits.</item>
               <item>Proteſtants <hi>and</hi> Papiſts.</item>
               <item>Officers <hi>and</hi> Souldiers.</item>
               <item>Meſſenger.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lady</hi> Lancarty.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:53309:3"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE</head>
            <lg>
               <l>AFter one Summers being in Arms in vain,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Ireland</hi> look't like <hi>Hounſlow-Heath</hi> Campaign:</l>
               <l>When to drink <hi>Uſquebagh,</hi> and pick his Toes,</l>
               <l>Mend his pacht <hi>Brogues,</hi> and Mundifie his Cloaths,</l>
               <l>Was all Teague had to do, one would have thought,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Iriſh</hi> might to Diſcipline been brought;</l>
               <l>For tho' their Wit and Senſe can never Charm ye,</l>
               <l>They might have learnt the Language of an Army:</l>
               <l>When their great Generals, fam'd beyond the Moon,</l>
               <l>Were Deputy King <hi>James,</hi> and Count <hi>Lazune.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The firſt, (for why ſhould we great Actions bury,)</l>
               <l>So famous for his Flight from <hi>Salisbury.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The other who from's Maſter learnt the Trick</l>
               <l>Of Burning Towns, becauſe they're Heretick:</l>
               <l>But they learnt only how to fight in jeſt,</l>
               <l>Nay, when they were by greateſt dangers preſt,</l>
               <l>And minding nothing that their Generals ſay,</l>
               <l>But how to face about and run away,</l>
               <l>Not Bullies Scouring from the Mid-Night Watch,</l>
               <l>Nor needy Debtor from a Serjeants Catch,</l>
               <l>Could Faſter run, than did the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Hoaſt.</l>
               <l>When Great King <hi>William</hi> o're the <hi>Boyn</hi> was croſt;</l>
               <l>Their Abdicated Prince firſt ſhow'd the way,</l>
               <l>And why ſhould they behind their Leader ſtay?</l>
               <l>For he, 'tis ſaid, from Hubbaboos and Hoots,</l>
               <l>Rode ſixty Mile that day, and ſpoil'd his Boots.</l>
               <l>'Twould be a Jubile at <hi>Rome that Day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If <hi>James</hi> could learn to fight, as well as Pray.</l>
               <l>And I'le affirm't without his Royal Word,</l>
               <l>'Tis a good Cauſe ſets th'edge upon a Sword.</l>
               <l>But his is ſuch a ſneaking little Cauſe,</l>
               <l>And much more <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>gly, then he made our Laws;</l>
               <l>A Cauſe of ſuch a Tottering ſinking Fame,</l>
               <l>No Prince e're thriv'd, that undertook the ſame;</l>
               <l>And were there but a worſer Place than Hell,</l>
               <l>May they be all ſent there, that wiſh it Well.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53309:3"/>
            <head>THE ROYAL FLIGHT: OR THE <hi>Conqueſt of Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT I.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>James, Tyrconnel, Herbert, Hall</hi> the Prieſt.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>K.</hi> James</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <stage>leaning his Arm upon a Table, and reſting his Head upon his Knuckles.</stage> IT was obſerv'd, that when I was firſt crown'd in this Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> my Crown ſtood like the Steeple of the <hi>Duomo</hi> at <hi>Piſa,</hi> awry upon my Head, which way ſoever Men lookt upon me. Was that a good Sign, <hi>Hall,</hi> or No?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſuppoſe it lean'd toward <hi>England,</hi> Sir, and then 'twas a good ſign—I long to be preaching again in your Chappel at <hi>White hall</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>By the Maſs, and ſo do I too, to hear thee there— But when I firſt turn'd Roman-Catholick, I was promis'd Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Gold. Where are thoſe Mountains?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Deſpair not, Sir; I make no Queſtion, but rather than you ſhall want, that Heaven will rain Gold for as many days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as it rain'd in the Time of the Flood.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:53309:4"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>I good Sooth, Father <hi>Hall,</hi> I ſhould be glad to ſee that day come—I have no Faith in Miracles—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>I am ſorry to hear you ſay ſo, Sir—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K. <hi>James.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Why ſo?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall</speaker>
                     <p>—Oh Sir—If you would but truſt in the Queen of Heaven, I dare be bold to ſay, ſhe would ſend you her own Life-Guard to fight without Pay—which would be the ſame thing, as if ſhe ſhould Coin half the Stars in the Firmament, to make Money for you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>In the mean time what good News, my Lords—How go Affairs in <hi>England</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>To your wiſh, Sir—The clos'd Parties are all to pieces again—Whigs and Tories once more at Daggers draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and contending for Mayors and Sheriffs, and Common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil-Men as much as ever—</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE II.</head>
                  <stage>Herbert, Tyrconnel, D'Avaux, Berwick, James.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>I know I have a good Party there—but ſtill my Brother of <hi>France</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold Sir—I am my Maſter's Repreſentative in this place, and muſt not brook this Language—My Brother of <hi>France.</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Why Sir, I am a Crown'd Head—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>That's nothing Sir, you are but his <hi>Viceroy</hi> in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom—conſequently none of his Brother—My Maſter's too Jealous of his Honour to call his Inferiour Brother—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrconnel.</speaker>
                     <p>By St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> y'are a Proud French-man—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>By St. <hi>Denis,</hi> y'are a Beggarly Teague—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Barwick.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir—the King is my Father—and my Father is the King of <hi>Frances</hi> Brother—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>Princock—you are too Sawcy— <stage>
                           <hi>Then turning to K.</hi> James.</stage> Sir, I demand Reparation for theſe Affronts—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, I'm ſorry for th'occaſion—I know indeed the Barons of my Exchequer at <hi>London</hi> may call Baron Tell-clock Brother, but Baron Tell-clock muſt not call any of them Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers—Y'are in the Right my Lord <hi>D'Avaux</hi>—I am but a King-Tell-clock in the World at preſent—But paſs it over— I'll undertake my Wife ſhall make all well again—</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53309:4"/>
                  <head>SCENE III.</head>
                  <stage>D'Avaux, Lauſun.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Morthleu!</hi> A Prince of No-land call my Maſter Brother!—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly, my Lord, I think 'twas by you ill tim'd—for you know our Maſter pretends to aſſiſt him as ſtill King of Great Brittain—and therefore I don't believe he would have diſown'd the Expreſſion as yet, had it been ſpoken to his Face—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>But I know as well how our Maſter intends to Fool him—how he only makes a Tool of him, but deſpiſes him in his Heart—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>That's nothing—what a Party would our Maſter looſe both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and perhaps in this Kingdom too—ſhould he pretend to ſet up for himſelf—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>To tell you truth, I think our Maſter does ill to ſpend ſo much Money, Time, and ſo many Men upon him—For i'my Conſcience 'twill all come to nothing—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>I am in a fine caſe then, to ſell ſo fair an Eſtate as I have done to follow his Fortune—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>Why look ye Sir—Where Prudence and Courage are wanting, there can never be a Proſpect of Succeſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>What muſt we do then?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>Make haſte while the Sun ſhines—Plunder and repay your ſelf, there be good Gleanings ſtill left—Never pity the People, they're a ſort of Miſcreants not worth hanging.— I have taken that courſe with the King, as to make him ſeize all his Proteſtant Subjects Goods by Armed Force, and then having ſet a Price upon them at his own Pleaſure, which he only pays in his own Copper Money, to export them to our Maſter his Dear Correſpondent in <hi>France.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>You are a Faithful and Politick Miniſter I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>Tann'd Hides, Raw Hides, Wooll, Tallow and Butter, are all Commodities which my Maſter wants—and how much of this ſort of Merchandize I have got the King to Ship off into <hi>France</hi> this year 1689 d'ye think?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>I cannot tell my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:53309:5"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar my Lord, no leſs than Thirty three thouſand four hundred fifty eight Hides Tann'd and Raw—Sixty one thouſand four hundred and five Stone of Wooll, three hundred eighty nine Tun of Tallow, and Forty Stone of Butter. Good Chaffer, my Lord, in <hi>France;</hi> as being all Staple Commodities, the Exportation of which Beggers the Proteſtants, the only Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious People of the Iſland, and Impoveriſhes the Kingdom; for which our Maſter makes no other Returns, but only Materials to Murder the Hereticks, and conquer the Nation for himſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Our Maſter, my Lord, I know is a Prudent Prince, and I make no queſtion but your Lordſhip has been able to carve ſufficiently for your ſelf out of ſuch Lumps as theſe—But when all's gone, what ſhall we have for our pains?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, my Lord, our Maſter does not intend to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the Land, there will be Arable and Paſture ſtill left—and you will have your Proportion you may be ſure—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith, my Lord, I would fain know which County will fall to my ſhare, becauſe I would be a little kind to my own Tenants—But letting this go—Did you ever ſee, my Lord, ſuch a Court as this? Not a Lady worth the Salute of <hi>Serviteur Madame</hi>—Their yellow Hair and Freckles would turn the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack of the moſt pumple-fac'd Whore-maſter in the World— A Man would rather let his Name periſh, then lye with 'em to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port his Family—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>Y'are a little too ſevere my Lord, 'tis true the <hi>Dublin</hi> Ladies want the Wit and Air, the Garb and Demeanour of our Pariſian <hi>Belles Filles,</hi> but there are ſome that will ſerve for all that, to keep a Man warm in a Froſty Night as well as the beſt—Then again, my Lord, there's a pleaſure in Variety—and many Men as well as my ſelf, love to ſee what Forraigners have got, as well as their own Native Country-women—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis very true, my Lord, and I would not willingly be beaten out of the Country, before I had try'd one of theſe Female <hi>Teagues</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>You have leiſure, my Lord—when you lye idle in your own Quarters, you have nothing to do but to be beating up the Womens Quarters—Look out ſharp, there's Game enough—I have ſo much buſineſs in my Head; I am ſo taken up with the Spirit of Politicks, that I have no time for Carnal Recreation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>I wiſh your Politicks Succeſs, my Lord—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:53309:5"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, Ay my Lord, if they ſucceed, we'll have French Ladies and Frenchified Ladies Hold Belly Hold—In the mean time I muſt go look after my Royal Charge—</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE IV.</head>
                  <stage>Hall <hi>the Jeſuit, and a Rabble of Prieſts, one carrying the Hoſt and another Tinkling a Little Bell before 'em.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 Prieſt.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mater Apoſtolorum, ora pro nobis</hi>—Singing—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 Prieſt.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <stage>[Whiſpering to his Companion]</stage>—S'life Joy make a great haſte—for by my Shoule, Joy, I have promis'd a Dear Joy to meet her by Twelve of the Clock—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By my Shoule I'm in thy Condition—<hi>Audi preces Noſtros pro Domino Noſtro Jacobo—bo—bo</hi>—Singing— <hi>Omnes. Regina Caeli, audi preces noſtros</hi>—Singing—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Sing Holy Men—pray Heartily Sons of Heav'n, and you ſhall ſee happy days—</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Omnes.</hi> again— <stage>[Tearing their Throats]</stage>—<hi>Regina Caeli audi pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces noſtros—pro Domino Jacobo—bo—bo—</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>And your Abbies and your Nunneries ſhall be reſtored to ye again.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Omnes</hi> again, <hi>Yo—He—Ba—bo—be—bo—bo—yo— He—bo—bo—bo—Au—men—</hi> Singing</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>And ye ſhall tread upon the Necks of the Hereticks—</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Omnes</hi> again, <hi>Yoh—heh—Ba—be—bo—ba—bo— Yoh—heh—ba—bo—bo—bo—Au—men—</hi> 
                        <stage>Singing.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>What did he ſay?—We ſhould have our Nunneries again?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Whiſpering together.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Ay marry did he—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Pray God he be <hi>John</hi>—For by my Shoule now, I am old Dog at a Forcible Entry—Heaven reſt my Father, who was a Bum-bayly, for teaching me—</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Omnes</hi> again —<hi>Yoh—Heh—ba—bo—be—be—ba— bo—Yoh—Heh—bo—ba—be—bo—Au—men</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall</speaker>
                     <p>—Av Holy Fathers—this Devotion will do the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks Buſineſs—We have a Great Work upon our Hands— Therefore do you labour with the Queen of Heaven—and I'll labour with our King upon Earth—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:53309:6"/>
                  <sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Omnes —Yoh—heh—ba—bo—be, be—ba—bo—Yoh Heb—bo—ba—bo—bo—bo—Au—men</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Well done Fathers, go on and proſper—Pray like Horſes—The Queen of Heaven knows all Languages, from the Holy Hebrew to the Prophane Pedlers French—Farewel—I am ſent for by the Defender of our Faith—</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE V.</head>
                  <stage>K. <hi>James, Hall, Tyrconnel, Nogent.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Where have you been, <hi>Hall,</hi> I have wanted thee this three hours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis a ſtrange thing, Sir, you can do nothing without me—I that was but a Cooks Son but t'other day, am now become your chief <hi>Achitophel</hi>—Where's your Great Father <hi>Peters?</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Hang him Fool and Knave—He has brought me to all this—Thou art all Inſpired—and talk'ſt like an Angel—Speak Bleſſed Oracle—I know thou haſt ſeen the Queen of Heaven in a Viſion laſt night—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>—I did ſo, Great Sir—and ſhe ſhew'd me your Majeſty juſt come into the World wrapt up in her own Smicket—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Father, Father, did ſhe tell you that ſhe would hide him in a Cloud in the day of Battel, as <hi>Venus</hi> did <hi>Eneas?</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>She did not ſay the ſame words—but her ſhewing him to me in that Poſture imply'd, ſhe would always protect him—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                     <p>The Heathen Oracles, Father, many times ſpeak Truth, but 'twas wrapt up in ſuch Ambiguous Lyes, that Men could never find it out—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nogent.</speaker>
                     <p>I wonder that ſuch a <hi>Bon-Catholick</hi> as you ſhould queſtion the Truth of what Father <hi>Hall</hi> ſays—You may as well call in doubt the Infallibility of our Holy Father the Pope.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Let every one believe as he pleaſes—You know 'tis my declar'd Opinion—But how ſhall a Man do to get ſo much into <hi>Venus</hi>'s Favour, as to be wrapt in a Cloud, in the time of Battel—I would fight then like a Dragon—tho if the Cloud be not Cannon-proof, I would not care a Fig for the Cloud neither—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:53309:6"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, 'tis the ſame thing to be under the Protection of the Queen of Heaven, as to be wrapt in <hi>Venus</hi>'s Cloud—For you ſhall be then encircled with Angels in ſuch a manner, that from what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Point of the Compaſs the Bullets come, they ſhall ſtand and catch them in their Hands, as the Maids do Stool-balls in the Holy-days.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Were I aſſur'd of this, I would Fight, as I ſaid before, like a Dragon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Nothing ſo ſure, Sir, if your Majeſty would but once be pleas'd to Fight—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll conſider of it—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>In the mean time a word with your Majeſty in private—</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VI.</head>
                  <stage>K. <hi>James, Hall</hi> the Prieſt.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, we have been praying for your Majeſties Succeſs like ſo many Cats upon the Tiles—We have and will make ſuch a hideous Noiſe, that certainly Heaven will anſwer our Requeſts, rather then be troubled with us—To tell you Truth, Sir, they wholly depend upon your Royal Word and Promiſes—So that were it not for hopes, their very Heart-ſtrings would crack with the pains which they take Day and Night, to teize Heav'n with their Caterwawling for your ſake—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>I know not that I ever gave them any cauſe ſince my Converſion to miſtruſt me—For tho I ne're regarded the keeping my word with Hereticks, I was always true to them—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Half the Revenue of this Iſland will be hardly ſufficient to reward them for the great care they take of your Affairs—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>I intend them no leſs—for I mean, if God proſper me, to have but two ſorts of Subjects in the World—Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Slaves—the One to ride me—the Other to be ridden by me—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Some People tell me, Sir, that I ſmell very ſtrong of an <hi>Archbiſhoprick</hi>—And when I ask 'em what ſort of ſmell that is, they Laugh—But then I tell 'em, I know not how an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhoprick ſmells,—only that I ſerve a Good and Gracious, Pious and Religious Maſter—a dutiful Son of the Church—a Promiſe-keeping Prince—And then a great many Laugh agen—but
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53309:7"/>then I tell 'em, let them Laugh that win—Did I not tell 'em right, an't like your Majeſty?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Nothing can ſtemm thy Prophetick Spirit, but my down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall—Thou might'ſt have told 'em, 'twas not the ſmell of an Archbiſhoprick, but of a Cardinals Hat with Toſſels—But heark thee me, <hi>Hall,</hi> art not thou Confeſſor to the Lady <hi>Lancarty?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes an't pleaſe your Majeſty for want of a better—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>I dye for love of that Lady—and you muſt uſe all the Charms of that <hi>Sacrament</hi> to bring her into my Embraces—Elſe I tell thee, I ſhall dye—and then all your Fat is in the Fire—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>—My dreaded Liege, I am not of that Opinion, that we muſt not do evil that good may come of it—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>By the way <hi>Hall.</hi> ſhe's marry'd—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>That's no Impediment at all Sir— <stage>[Aſide.]</stage> Now I ſmell a Cardinals Hat indeed—You are a Prince ſo Brave, ſo Generous, ſo Valiant, ſo Renown'd, ſo Vertuous, ſo Pious, ſo punctual an Obſerver of that Maxim, do as you would be done to, that 'tis Pitty the World ſhould not be ſtockt with your Royal Breed—Upon the Word of a Prieſt, Dread Sovereign, the Sacrament of Confeſſion ſhall lore Bonnet to all other Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions but this—The Sacrament of Confeſſion ſhall ſerve you to the uttermoſt of its Power—Who would be ſuch an Infidel, as not to Pimp for the Holy Church?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>—Tell her—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Tell her my Liege!—I'll tell her 'tis the Queen of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens Pleaſure—and ſhe muſt do it—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Were it nothing elſe, this Complacency of thine will raiſe thee—go and be ſpeedy in the Affair.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>She Confeſſes to morrow—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſooner the better—But be ſure of Secrecy—S'life—if my Tyranneſs ſhould know it, I ſhould never be able to protect the firſt Perriwig I appear'd before her in—and perhaps another Black Eye to boot—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſee the Rock, and ſhall avoid it, Sir—</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53309:7"/>
                  <head>SCENE VII.</head>
                  <stage>Lauſun, La Hoquette, Count de Leri, Nugent.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <stage>[To Lauſun having a Book in his hand]</stage> What, my Lord, Bookiſh this Morning—I ſuppoſe there's no body here that needs to hear Lectures of Martial Diſcipline—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar, Millord, me ha ſold de very great Eſtate vor de King of <hi>Englan</hi>'s ſake—and me muſt get de very great Eſtate by do King—Begar dis booken ſhew me de very fine tings—'tis de Preſent Eſtat of <hi>Englan</hi>—Begar me no beaga without Booka—me kenow vat me Beaga, bevore me open my Mout—Begar—me no be deny'd—me no Fight de ſtroke, bevore de King make me de Promiſe under his Haund of de great Matre—Begar here be de Lord High Mareſchall—vat is dat de value—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent.</speaker>
                     <p>That's a place of much more Honour then Profit.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar me no care vor de great Onor, me be vor de Profeet—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>So be mee too Begar—Let me ſee your Book a delittle Millord—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold—Let me ſhooze in de firſt place a—den take a de Book among you—Here is de Lord Shanſelour's place—de Fee 848 Pound per de year—Begar me no accept of de eight hundred vorty eight Pound by de year—Me ha ſold a great deal muſh more Begar—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar den me vil ave it—Begar me get a nautre, and a nautre if dat vill not ſerve a—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent.</speaker>
                     <p>The Lord Chancellor's place and the Judges are only for Lawyers my Lord—they muſt be left for ſuch as us to ſhare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar me no care for de Law—me put in de Deputy vor de Law—Begar de King himſelf is but our Maitre's Deputy—Begar and de Engliſh and de Iris be no more den de Deputies to de Franſhe Man de Mereet—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count de Leri.</speaker>
                     <p>Here is de Lord Brevie de Seale—Fee vife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred poun par l'an—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:53309:8"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lords—you had better look among the Men of Great Titles—there you will find Forfeitures anow to beg—Theſe Places are but for Life—but Land will deſcend to your Poſterity—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar here is de Duke a de <hi>Beaufort</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay now y'have hit it—there's a Man enjoys more Land of his own than Forty Marquiſſes of <hi>France</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Den here is de Earl of <hi>Bedford</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay marry Sir, there's another has more than all the Peers of <hi>France</hi> put together—but 'tis a great part of it Abby Lands, perhaps the King will reſtore it to the Church.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar—me no care de ruſh for de Shurch—let dem take a de Lord Shancellors, and de Lord Privy Seals places dat vill—me ave de Duke of <hi>Beauforts</hi> and de Earl of <hi>Bedfords</hi> places—Begar—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent.</speaker>
                     <p>What both?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>I Begar—boat—Begar—me go preſantly to de King—an me beaga deſe two places Begar—And Begar he give em me too—or me no Fight a ſtroke Begar—</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VIII.</head>
                  <stage>K. <hi>James, Lauſun, La Hoquette, Count de Leri.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar, Sir, me be come here—me leave a me Native Country to ſerve your Majeſtee—me ſell very much Land Begar for your ſake—me come here to reſtore you to your Trone—Begar me deſerve de very much Recompanſe—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Gratitude, my Lord, is a Virtue which I always boaſted to be Maſter of—and therefore you may reſt aſſur'd of a Reward anſwerable to your Services.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun</speaker>
                     <p>—Begar Sir, me no love de General—me love to come to de Particular—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, any particular Requeſt of yours in reaſon is granted—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Why den—an pleaſe your Majeſte, me ſall expect for my good Service de Duke of <hi>Beauford's</hi> and de Earl of <hi>Bedford</hi>'s places—Begar doſe two places me expect or me no Fight a ſtroke Begar—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:53309:8"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>I know no places they ever had Sir—Indeed the one was Preſident of <hi>Wales</hi>—but that's more Honour than Profit, my Lord—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar me be told dey ave a more Land den all de Peers de <hi>France</hi> a.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh now I underſtand you—You beg the Eſtates of theſe two Perſons—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>I Begar—de Eſtates—me hope your Majeſtee wont let a me be ſheated for no ſpeak good Engliſh—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>By no means my Lord, and you have my Royal Word for't—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar me no take a de word—Dey ſay you no ſo good as your word—dey ſay, dat had a you kept your Promiſe wid a your Subject, you no need of come here—Begar—me ave it under a your Hand and Seal Begar—or me no Fight un ſtroke a Begar—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, I ſhall take order to give you all the Satisfaction you can deſire—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>Pleaſe your Majeſtee, you muſt expect to be troubled with more Petiſhioners o dis kind—but as you have many to ask, ſo you have much to diſpoſe of—All your Subject vill be de Traytors Begar—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>And I'll ſwinge 'em off for a Company of Hereticks too, if ever I get among 'em again—But they that ſerve me in my Extremities, ſhall eat Gold—they ſhall not ask ſo faſt as I'll give—Can you think of nothing Monſieur?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, me beg by de book—me beg de Gran Shan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors place—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>That's for a Lawyer, not for a Man of the Sword—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>Den gi' me de Arſhbiſhop de <hi>Canterbury</hi>'s place—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>That's for a Divine—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette</speaker>
                     <p>—O Sir—me put in de fine Deputees—me get de monee—me no care for de Law nor de Goſpel neder—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>De Leri.</speaker>
                     <p>My Suit is for de Gran Treaſurers place—and I make no doubt, but wat wid my Panſion, and wat me ſhall ſheat your Majeſtee, me ſhall do vell anough—I would not give a ruſh for de Treaſurer that knows not how to lick his own Fingers—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James</speaker>
                     <p>—Look ye my Lords—I don't love much trouble—'een be your own Carvers your ſelves—Do you but take care of me and my Little Son—and then, take and do what ye will—For to tell you the Truth, I don't care a Farthing what becomes of my Subjects—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:53309:9"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>De Leri.</speaker>
                     <p>Wy Sir, you know y'ave made our Maſter a Promiſe to deſtroy de Heretic—and Begar your Subject be de Grand He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retic i'de Varle—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis very true—and therefore do you act your parts like Men of Valour—and then—Boys—</p>
                     <p>If by your Courage I am e're reſtor'd,</p>
                     <p>I'll make 'em know that I can keep my word.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>ACT II.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>K. <hi>James, Tyrconnel, Nugent, Powis.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Tyrconnel <hi>reading a Letter.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>THE P. of <hi>O.</hi> has certainly compleated his Levies, and will be in <hi>Ireland</hi> in leſs than a Fortnight—In the mean time King <hi>James</hi>'s Friends are hard at work—In the mean time the Cock-match goes on—the Black-coats promiſe—and you would not think how briskly the young Fry Gabber at <hi>Samm</hi>'s Coffee-houſe—So ſoon as the P. is got over the Water we fairly begin—We have great hopes the E. of <hi>T.</hi> will fail their Expectations, and leave 'em i' the Lurch, when they leaſt expect it—'Twill be ſuch a Blow as will make their Hearts ake—The King of <hi>France</hi>'s Declaration has wrought ſtrange Effects, and reconcil'd him to abundance of Gulls—The Five Biſhops ſtand ſtoutly to their Pan-pudding—Come, come, Sir, 'Tis a long day that never has an end—'Tis Mony that makes the Mare to go—He that has the longeſt Sword governs the World—And a light Wind ſhakes no Corn—</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To King</hi> James—</stage>
                  <p>Thus you ſee, Sir, all things go trim and trickfie for you in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi>—Your work will be done to your hand—</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, Ay,—But what ſhall we do with this ſame Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>—I fear me you will find him a Sower Crab Orange—I ha found him ſo to my Coſt—and you know the Proverb—Hang a Dog upon a Crab-tree, and he'll never love Varjuice—And for my part I am forced to abſtain from Veal, leaſt they ſhould bring Oranges to the Table—the very ſight of 'em makes me ready to Puke—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:53309:9"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent</speaker>
                     <p>—Oh Sir—the Queen of Heaven is a' your ſide—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>I had rather have another <hi>Joan</hi> of <hi>Arque</hi> o'my ſide by half—One Amazon upon Earth is worth twenty ſhe Saints in Heaven—'Tis true ſhe was burnt for a Witch—but for all that ſhe turn'd the Fortune of <hi>France.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent.</speaker>
                     <p>Heavens! Sir—we never heard you talk at this rate before—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>I tell ye, I am angry with the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> becauſe ſhe would not give a Bleſſing to my Endeavours upon my Wife—and yet I gave her the beſt Bodkin that ever ſhe wore in her Life—So that had not ſome been wiſer than ſome, I might have digg'd up all the Parſley Beds i'the Kingdom, before I ſhould have lit upon a Boy ſo fit for my purpoſe—I am diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compos'd—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Powis.</speaker>
                     <p>What think you (Sir) of retiring back to <hi>France</hi> for a while—For ſome People have made an Obſervation, that none of your Deſigns thrive where you are in Perſon—You have found the one pretty true by Experience—try tother way—and let us alone to Fortune by our ſelves—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Fortunes a Whig and a Draggle-tail—If St. <hi>Patrick</hi> won't aſſiſt his own Teagues, and St. <hi>Denis</hi> ſtand by his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men, I am loſt—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Powis.</speaker>
                     <p>This Deſpair of yours will diſcourage your Souldiers—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, my Lord—I don't deſpair neither—You ſee I venture my Perſon among you—and that I think is ſufficient to ſhew that I have Courage—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I have read i'the Story of <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, how <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh fought <hi>Richard</hi> the Third and ſlew him—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſo, my Lord, you'd have me fight the P. of <hi>O</hi>—I thank ye my Lord for your Parallel—I'll do any thing in Perſon but that—You know that <hi>Richard</hi> the Third was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a Tyrant, as I am accounted—and <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh the Deliverer of the People—Now then, my Lord, if the Parallel hold, 'tis the P. of <hi>O.</hi> that muſt Kill me, and Not I the P. of <hi>O</hi>—I thank ye my Lord for your good Advice, but I ſhan't take it—Is there no way to beat the P. of <hi>O.</hi> but by my fighting him in Perſon?—Muſt I do your Drudgery for ye? As if there were not anow to fight him in Perſon beſides me—Gad do you fight him in Perſon your ſelf, if you like fighting in Perſon ſo well—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, if you let him paſs the <hi>Newry,</hi> he'll preſently be with ye at the <hi>Boyne</hi>—and if he get over that Paſſage, then farewel Froſt Y' faith—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:53309:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Bodies are the Walls I truſted to, to guard thoſe Paſſes—and becauſe I did not think ye all <hi>Guy</hi>'s of <hi>Warwick,</hi> St. <hi>Georges,</hi> and <hi>Palmerins</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> I got my Brother of <hi>France</hi> to aſſiſt ye—What would ye have me do?—'Tis not for Kings to expoſe their Royal Perſons—If I am loſt, all's loſt—Tye all the curſed Proteſtants Neck and Heels together, and Pile 'um up i'the way as high as the middle Region—Surely that will ſtop his Highneſs for ſome time—If that won't do, the Lord have Mercy upon us—However if the worſt come to the worſt, I have one Shift left me ſtill, that I can run faſter than his Highneſs can follow me—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Heavens Bleſs us! don't talk of running yet Sir; if you do, you'll ſet your Souldiers a running as faſt as Sheep—You muſt appear among 'em, and hearten 'em up with your Preſence—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>If that be all, that ſhall be done I warrant ye—I can ride about, and look like <hi>Hector</hi> himſelf where there's no danger—as you ſhall preſently ſee—Let my Horſe be got ready—</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Repreſenting the Iriſh Camp, the King riding about and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf to the Souldiers, attended by</hi> Tyrconnel, Powis, Sarsfeild, Herbert <hi>and others.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>What Fellow is that with a Crows Neſt about his Chops?—and a Mouth as wide as a Sawpit—He looks as if he were able to eat up a whole Regiment of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Men—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, Sir, have you forgot your Friend <hi>Teague Oregan,</hi> your deſign'd Governour of <hi>Charlemont?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Is that he?—Heark ye me, Fellow Souldier—can you hold out a ſtrong Town?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Teague.</speaker>
                     <p>I by my Shoule can I, to ſerve your Majeſty— tho by my Shoule, Dear Joy, I will not make a promiſe to hold it out to the eating of Dogs and Cats, becauſe Bonny Clapper and Conny Rapper agrees better with my Stomack—But if no Enemy appear before the Town—If I meet with no Mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſhions of Bombs and Granadoes, and ſuch other Diabolical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Death—I will hold out your Majeſties Town as long as <hi>Neſtor</hi> liv'd—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:53309:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>That is a pleaſant Fellow, I warrant him—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, and as Stout as ever <hi>Knock Fergus</hi> himſelf. He only talks to make your Majeſty merry—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Teague.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay by my Shoule do I—For by my Shoule I admire and adore your Majeſty for your Grandeur and Puiſhance, as being Tenant <hi>in Capite</hi> to the Frenſh King for three large Provinſhes of this flouriſhing and populouſh Iſland: and then for your extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary goodneſs in taking upon you to be the Sharitable Defender of the Roman Catholic Reliſhion, to the loſs of almoſt three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms—tho I have no Religion at all—for that my Dear Joy makes a Man Coward-hearted—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>[Aſide to</hi> Tyr.]</stage> I fear this is not the Man you take him to be.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Nere doubt him, Sir—I have ſeen him eat a Dagger to the Haft, meerly becauſe it would not enter a Musket-proof Breaſt-plate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Teague.</speaker>
                     <p>I muſt confeſh, Dear Joy, that ſom Conſideraſhions at ſom time may mortifie my Couraſh, ſo that if I meet a Party of the Enemie three times leſs than my own, I may be perſwaded to run for't; not out of any fear of my Shoule, Dear Joy, but becauſh the beſt Governour i' the World may ſometimes have a Qualm come over his Stomack, a <hi>jay ne ſcay quoy,</hi> that will daunt the Spirit of <hi>Ajax</hi> himſelf. Which Devil of a <hi>jay ne ſcay Quoy,</hi> if it ſhould ſeize me when the Enemy comes before your Majeſties Town, I cannot be poſhitive in the Reſoſolutions I may be forc'd to take—beſides a natural Antipathy which I have againſt <hi>Storming</hi>—For when an Enemy takes a Town by Storm, he puts all to the Sword—and I would be more tender of your Maſheſties Subjects—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou ſpeakeſt like a Chriſtian, and I took thee for a Souldier—well, come to my Tent at Night—</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The King riding on meets</hi> Sarsfeild, <hi>to whom</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <p>How now <hi>Sarsfeild,</hi> how goes the World—Are your Men in Heart? They ſay the P. of <hi>O.</hi> is coming to give me a Viſit—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsfeild.</speaker>
                     <p>Luſty and Brave, Sir—they have all vow'd to ſave your Majeſty the Expence of Belly-Timber, and to feed upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Danes</hi> and <hi>Dutch-men</hi> as long as there is one alive—and as for the <hi>Inniskillen</hi> Men, they have Sworn to dry 'em up in their Chimneys for Relliſhing Bits i'the Winter—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Bravely reſolv'd—this comforts my Heart again—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsfeild.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, as I was walking the Rounds t'other night, I heard a Noiſe in one of the Suttlers Tents, where ſome of my Souldiers were Drinking your Majeſties Health in Snap-dragons—which made me ſtand ſtill to liſten—And your Majeſty cannot imagine how many ſorts of Oaths they Swore, what they would do to ſerve your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53309:11"/>if ever the P. of O. came into this Kingdom—One ſwore <hi>Walſingham</hi>—another ſwore like a Lord—another ſwore like a Tinkar—I have ſome Men under my Command, that if words would do it, will make all the Fat in a Church-yard tremble— I have others that eat Iron Wagons—Kill all they ſee, and eat all they Kill—I have another Regiment of young ſtout Fellows that are all in Love up to the Hard Ears, and Fight meerly to win their Miſtreſſes Favours—You need no more fear the P. of O. than I fear a good Dinner—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>S'life, Sir, this Army can never be beaten; this is an Army not of Men but of <hi>Termagaunts</hi>—Now one <hi>Termagaunt</hi> is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than twenty <hi>Croats</hi>—and twenty <hi>Croats</hi> are better than forty <hi>Tartars</hi>—and forty <hi>Tartars</hi> are better than fourſcore <hi>Danes</hi> or <hi>Dutch</hi>— by which Computation one of your <hi>Termagaunts</hi> will beat eight ſcore of the P. of O's Souldiers—However if you are afraid of the Leaves never go to the Wood—but keep in your Caſtle of <hi>Dublin</hi>— there ſit in Counſel, receive Intelligence, and give out Orders— Let them Fight—do you Deſign and Advize—Policy many times is better than Strength—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>No, not ſo far neither—I'll be within call howe're the world goes—'tis but having a good Horſe always ready Bridi'd and Saddl'd—A Man may be ſaid to be preſent, if he be but within the ſmell of his Army—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Souldiers ſhout—Volleys from all Parts.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsfeild.</speaker>
                     <p>Brave Boys—Brave Boys—Ay marry Sir—here's Muſick for ye—Is not this better than all your Chappel Gliſter-pipes?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou wilt never leave thy Prophaneneſs—<hi>Sarsfeild</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsfeild.</speaker>
                     <p>Now you look like <hi>Jove</hi> with all his Thunder about him—</p>
                     <stage>Shout again—Volleys again.</stage>
                     <stage>And then throws up his Hat.</stage>
                     <p>Hey—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <stage>[Aſide]</stage> This Fellow will make me valiant I think, in ſpight of my Teeth.
<stage>[Aloud]</stage> Ay marry—this is like my Muſtring upon <hi>Hounſlow-Heath</hi>—I could live and dye with ſuch merry Boys as theſe—were this the worſt of it—Well, I would not for a Cow of a Groat, but have ſeen and heard what I have heard and ſeen this day—and now let all the Devils in Hell ſay nay, I am reſolv'd to have one Bruſh for't—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Powis.</speaker>
                     <p>This, Sir, is like your Victorious Brother of <hi>France</hi>—He never comes near danger no more than you do—but he rides about, and puts Life into his Souldiers, and then gets aloof off—You can't imagine what an Encouragement 'tis to an Army; to have a King aloof off—And then when the Danger's over, you may gallop in among 'em and ſpit i'their Mouths, and have all the Honour of the Day attributed to your Valour—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53309:11"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>That's but reaſon, my Lotd—your Counſel's good—and I aſſure ye my Lord, this day has got me two Stomacks—one to Eat, and t'other to Fight—but let's eat firſt—there's no ſuch haſt for t'other.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE III.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Hall</hi> the Prieſt, Lady <hi>Lancarty.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>That's nothing Madam, where the Holy Church impoſes a Command, you are to make no Scruples—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <p>Surely Father, you do not talk as you mean—Did the Holy Church ever command a Woman to commit Adultery?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>No, Madam, nor did the Holy Church ever command a Woman to commit Murder—And yet you ſee that for the good of the Holy Church <hi>Judith</hi> cut off <hi>Holophernes</hi>'s Head—Nor is it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great Probability from the Effect, that ſhe let him have the uſe of her Body to boot—for you ſee that he had tired himſelf—that is, he had overwrought himſelf through the Allurements of a freſh Beauty and fell aſleep—Thus you ſee, Madam, here was Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Murder and Treachery, three Fowl Sins, 'tis true—but being impos'd upon <hi>Judith</hi> by the Neceſſities of the Jewiſh Church, ſhe was not only acquitted by the Church, but highly applauded for what ſhe had done—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <p>But Father, I do not ſee the Holy Church in any ſuch danger at preſent—Where are the <hi>Holophernes</hi>'s that threaten to ruin the Holy Church?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, here is a Great Monarch, upon whom all the Hopes of the Holy Church in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> depend—This Great Monarch Sues to you for the Trifle of a nights Lodging— Now upon your denial, this Great Monarch, not able to bear the Croſs of his Ardent Affection, dies—and what follows?—All the Hopes of the Holy Church are thereby loſt for ever—and you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd to Eternal Purgatory—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <p>—Father, Thoſe of your Order are notable Sophiſters— but you ſhall never argue me out of my Honour—I ſay again, the Holy Church never commanded a Woman to commit Adultery—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Lord Madam, that you will not underſtand—when I ſay the Holy Church, I mean the Intereſt of the Holy Church—For the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Holy Church and the Holy Church are all one—Now Madam, when the Intereſt of the Holy Church requires it, you are bound to do whatever may contribute to the Advancement of her intereſt—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:53309:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <p>I cannot be of your Opinion, Father—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, I muſt chide you for your Squeamiſhneſs—what Injury will it be?—For grant it were a Sin—you know the Church can give you Abſolution—Now then where you receive no Injury, to pretend Conſcience to the Prejudice of the Holy Church!—Madam, I wonder at ye.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <p>I know Father that you can Abſolve me—but will my Husband forgive me?—You know Father there was a great Lady in <hi>France</hi> that went into <hi>England,</hi> and returned back into <hi>France,</hi> but was Poyſon'd in three days after ſhe got home.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Husband! Madam—why Confeſſors of my Order don't uſe to be Blabs of their Tongues—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <p>I don't know Father how it comes to paſs—but when Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men do thoſe things, the Devil ſtill ows 'em a ſhame—and all the Town rings on't the next day—who d'ye think told that Ladies Husband?—her ſelf?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall</speaker>
                     <p>—Madam—I tell ye Madam, you ſtand in your own Light— and why is't?—becauſe you are afraid to Cuckold your Husband— Now I affirm that you don't Cuckold your Husband—For Kings are not Men, but Gods—Now I ſay it can be no Defilement to a Mortal Husbands Bed, for his Wife to lye with a Deity—<hi>ergo</hi>— And thus <hi>Alcmena</hi> could not be ſaid to Cuckold <hi>Amphitryo,</hi> becauſe ſhe did not lye with a Man, but with <hi>Jupiter,</hi> that was a God— <hi>ergo</hi> again—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſee, Father, you leave no Stone unturn'd—But are you ſure the King dyes for love of me—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Ah—Madam, d'ye think I come to tell ye a <hi>Canterbury</hi> Story—or that I would appear in ſuch an Office as this, but to ſerve our Holy Mother the Church?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly Father, I cannot tell what to ſay to the Buſineſs— the Devil and you are two Prevailing Tempters—But are you ſure the King dyes for Love of me?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Sure! Madam—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <p>I would not for a Thouſand Pounds, the King ſhould dye for Love of me—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>A Thouſand Pounds! Madam—why 'tis as much as your Life's worth—you may be impeach'd of High Treaſon upon it—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then Father 'tis reſolv'd—neither will I dye for the King, neither ſhall the King dye for me—I find my ſelf in a tottering condition—Were his Majeſty but here himſelf now, he might puſh me down with the end of his Foreſinger—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:53309:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis a Heaven upon Earth, Madam, to be a Great Monarch's Miſtreſs—I have heard of One who had a Thouſand Pound brought her every Munday Morning to Play at Cards with—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <p>That's more than I expect—'tis in Obedience to our Holy Mother the Church that I ſubmit—But Privacy's the Word, Father—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Bleſſed Lady, be aſſur'd of that—My Boſom is a Cabinet not to be unlockt with Keys of Torment, when entruſted with Secrets of this Nature—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <stage>[Aſide]</stage> A moſt excellent Pimp—would I had known thee ſooner—Well then, Father, I leave the reſt to your diſcreet Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance—For you know the Saying, Tho Tw. be not Coy, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation is Nice—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>By the way Madam, one thing more—when the Crowned Head lyes groveling at your Feet, and bathing your Knees with his Tears—remember me, Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <p>A Labourer like you is worthy of his Hire—farewel, Father</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE IV.</head>
                  <stage>Hall, <hi>K.</hi> J. <hi>Groom of the Chamber.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Now do I go to wait upon the King with a Conſcience void of Offence—Thanks be to Heaven, I have diſcharged a Great Truſt, and that Faithfully and Effectually too—By ſuch ways as theſe do thoſe of our Order inſinuate themſelves into the Courts of Kings, and govern the Hearts of Princes—The Miſs is our Slave, and the Prince is Hers—Thus we command his Secrets, ruin our Enemies, and preſerve our own Grandeur—Thus Father <hi>Le Chaiſe</hi> governs <hi>Madam de Monteſpane,</hi> and ſhe governs <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. ſhe commands the Hereticks to be deſtroy'd, and her word's a Law— And that which waſhes our Conſciences with Hyſſop is this, that all this is done to advance the Intereſt of the Holy Mother the Church— But I delay too long to carry the Good News to the King—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>To the Groom of the Chamber.</stage>
                  <p>Sir, is his Majeſty awake?—</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Groom.</speaker>
                     <p>Quite the Contrary, Sir—He is faſt aſleep—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Wake him then, for I have Buſineſs of Importance to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to him—tell him I am here, and that will be your War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of Security—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Groom.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <stage>[To himſelf]</stage> Pox o' this Raſcally Prieſt, now muſt I go wake the King to hear ſome impertinent Lecture or other for eating Roaſt beef of a Friday—Are you ſo much in haſte, Father, you can't ſtay till the King wakes of himſelf?—He was up late laſt night—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:53309:13"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>—Sir, Company will then preſs in—my buſineſs is private—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Groom.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <stage>[To himſelf]</stage> Some Pimping Story or other, Begad—and then I'll not hinder it—</p>
                     <stage>Goes in and comes out again.</stage>
                     <p>Father, the King's awake, and gives you leave to enter—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Shuts the Door after him.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Father, you have wak'd me out of a ſweet Slumber— I was juſt dreaming of the Lady you wot of—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis from her I bring you Tidings— I wiſh all your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were as much at your command as She—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt Excellent Father—ſit down—and talk ſoftly—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I gave her a Viſit under the uſual pretence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion—according to your command—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>And did you find her laden with Sin—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>I ne're asked her Sir, how many Sins ſhe had committed— my buſineſs was, as you well know, had they been a hundred, to perſwade her to commit half a Score more, to ſerve your Majeſty— and then to give her a Diſcharge in full—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>And how did ſhe reliſh your Diſcourſe Father?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Why Sir I laid before her the Danger that threaten'd the Holy Church, if ſhe ſhould ſuffer you to Languiſh and Pine away to Death for Love of her—I told her how you had loſt your Stomack, and that nothing would go down with you but Sugar ſops at night— How you faſted and pray'd Mundays, Tueſdays, Wedneſdays, Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days, Fridays and Saturdays; and that I was confident ſhe was the Saint, to whom you offer'd up all your Devotions—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſaid ſhe?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>She Hector'd and Flounc'd at firſt, as if ſhe had been the Goddeſs of Chaſtity—call'd me Pimping Prieſt, and a Reproach to my Profeſſion—and held out her Flag of Defiance at that rate— that I began to deſpair of taking the Fort—but the Devil ſo Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſupply'd me with freſh Batteries, that at length, as I may ſo ſay, I took her by Storm—And when ſhe ſurrender'd—<hi>But does the King dye for me,</hi> ſhe cry'd, with ſuch a Languiſhing Utterance, that I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived I had wounded her to the Heart in the Aſſault, and that ſhe only expected you to be her Surgeon—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Succeſsful Father—thou haſt oblig'd us for ever—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>She enjoyn'd me Sir, moſt ſeriouſly to Privacy—and I found too ſhe had read the Earl of <hi>Rocheſter</hi>'s Poems—for ſhe made uſe of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Clevelands</hi> Argument—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>That, Father, muſt be another of your Maſter-pieces—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>And I think Sir, I have it already—I will go to her again, and appoint a convenient Time and Hour for Confeſſion—which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53309:13"/>being done with all the Care and Caution imaginable, you ſhall go and meet her in my Habit—Our Habit is a ſtrange ſort of Habit, Sir—the Devil makes uſe of it ſometimes to cover his Clov'n Feet—A Jeſuits Gown is like <hi>Ixions</hi> Cloak, which <hi>Juno</hi> gave him to lye with her undiſcover'd—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>By the Maſs, Father, thou haſt Wit and Invention at Will—I hug thy Deſign—and I like it the better, becauſe you know I am one of the Order my ſelf—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir you ſee I am wholly at your Devotion—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Nor ſhall you looſe by't, Father—<hi>Croeſus</hi> ſhall not be richer than Thee, if e're I come to my Throne again—More than that, I will erect a Colledge of Jeſuits in <hi>England</hi> as big as the Eſcurial in <hi>Spain</hi>—There ſhalt thou live like a Prince—have more Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips than the Old Abbots of St. <hi>Albans,</hi> and Eat and Drink in more Plenty than the Monks of <hi>Glaſſenbury</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe are Spurs would make a Malt-horſe fly like a <hi>Pegaſus</hi>— Alas Sir, my Ambition aims not at theſe great things—The World well knows your great Zeal to advance the Glory of the Holy Order—And that's the main Spur that quickens me to your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice—I have my Leſſon Sir—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Bowes and goes off.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE V.</head>
                  <stage>Lauſun, La Hoquette, Count de Leri.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <stage>[Reading a Letter]</stage> I am certainly inform'd, that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> will ſuddenly be in <hi>Ireland</hi> with a great Army—Therefore if your Affairs do not ſucceed in that Kingdom, be ſure to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of K. <hi>James,</hi> and haſten his ſafe return into <hi>France</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>Our Maſter's a Wiſe King—but why he ſhould be ſo chary of an Unfortunate Prince, is paſt my Apprehenſion— <hi>Diable</hi>—I am ſorry he is not in <hi>France</hi> at this preſent—For never any thing proſper'd where-ever he was—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>If you do not apprehend it, I do—there's no ſuch Myſtery but may be eaſily unfolded—Should he be too Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate he would be too Rampant for our Maſter—Let him be Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate—but ſtill preſerve him in his Misfortunes—and at one time or other he may chance to do our Maſters work—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mortbleu</hi>—What a power of Mony has he coſt our Maſter already to no purpoſe—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Th'art a Fool, my Maſter has not ſpent a Doit upon him—all our Maſter has ſpent, has been for his own Intereſt—
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53309:14"/>Had it not been for our Maſters pretended aſſiſting him in this Kingdom, and by that means cutting out other work for the P. of O. we ſhould have had that Encroaching Enemy of ours at <hi>Verſailles</hi> before this—And beſides, if our Maſter get this Kingdom under this pretence, 'tis all clear Gains and Mony well laid out—You know what he Conquers is all his own—let the Pretence be what it will—If our Maſter thought the Kingdom of Heaven worth Having, he has Pen-men that would derive his Pedigre in a direct Line from the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> rather than he ſhould want a Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion—In ſhort K. <hi>James</hi> muſt be a Goad in the ſides of the Engliſh as long as he lives—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mortbleu,</hi> then let our Maſter find out a Goad that will peirce to the Quick, and not ſuch a Goad without a Point as K. <hi>James</hi>—Let him ſet up his Son, the Young P. of <hi>Wales</hi>—Fortune's a Whore, and loves Young Fleſh better than Old—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no—There are none in <hi>England</hi> but thoſe of our own Religion that believe that Farce—King <hi>J.</hi> has been Crown'd in that Kingdom, and the Proteſtant Jeſuits of his Party have found out a quaint Diſtinction already of a King <hi>de Jure</hi> and <hi>de Facto,</hi> to make a Broyl upon the Coaſt, and divide the Allegiance of the People— 'Tis for this our Maſter is ſo chary of K. <hi>James</hi>—otherwiſe he would not care whither the Cham of <hi>Tartary,</hi> or the Great <hi>Mogul</hi> were King of <hi>England,</hi> 'twere all one to Him—Our Maſter's a Charitable Monarch, and if any Forreign Prince in his Diſtreſs, craves his Aſſiſtance, there is no Man ſo ready to lay hold of the Opportunity—The Fox deſir'd the Lamb but only to let him put in his Head, and then he knew well enough how to get in his whole Body—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, I know our Maſter knows how to make uſe of a proper Tool as well as any Prince in <hi>Europe</hi>—But what would he do with this Iſland if he had it?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Why Tranſplant all the Cowardly Iriſh to his Plantations in <hi>America,</hi> and People the Kingdom with his own Subjects—Or what if he ſhould Diſpeople the Country and leave it without Inhabitants?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>I confeſs 'tis a good way to prevent Rebellion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>You know our Maſter loves to be King of Countries with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out People—and that made him Depopulate the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and the reſt of his Conqueſts in <hi>Germany</hi>—Nay you ſee how he Diſpeoples his own <hi>France</hi> it ſelf—By the way, he learnt that piece of Policy of the Turk—And ſo if he could but get footing in <hi>England,</hi> you ſhould ſoon ſee what a <hi>Hunting field</hi> K. <hi>J.</hi> and He would make of it—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53309:14"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mortbleu,</hi> there's reaſon for that—'tis a Hive of Hereticks that ought to be ſmoak'd to Death with Brown Paper and wet Straw—But do you believe the P. of O. is a coming indeed?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Our Maſter you ſee believes it, and trembles already for his Brother of <hi>England</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leri.</speaker>
                     <p>I don't like that ſame Diabolical Faith of our Maſter— 'tis ominous—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>Nor do I love Fighting in an Iſland—'tis like <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbag</hi> and the Gyants Fighting in a Sawpit—I love the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent-Liberty where a Man may run as far as he pleaſes—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leri.</speaker>
                     <p>However our Maſter could not have given us a fairer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to run away with Honour, had he ſtudy'd five years— Nor indeed do I ſee any reaſon why we ſhould venture our Lives and our Limbs with an Engliſh King that won't venture with us—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>In ſhort Gentlemen, we are bound to fight for our Honour—and we muſt ſave the King to obey our Maſter—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leri.</speaker>
                     <p>But if I be kill'd, how can I ſave the King?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauſun.</speaker>
                     <p>Therein you muſt uſe your Diſcretion—A good Souldier may fight with Diſcretion—and make an honourable Retreat both at the ſame time—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>And you ſhall ſee Noble General, how diſcreetly we'll ſplit a Hair between our Martial Honour and our Obedience to our Maſter—our Lives for yours, we'll either Fight diſcreetly, or retreat diſcreetly—But a Pox of retreating—I ſcorn to retreat—Now I think on't, I can kill a hundred at a time for my own ſhare, and fight with diſcretion—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leri.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, if ye go to that, I know not how many hundred I may kill when I am thoroughly heated—for I remember I kill'd Forty once with my own hand in cold Blood—No, I'll never retreat unleſs I'm hard put to't—but if the Devil and Neceſſity drive me—then I muſt obey my Maſter—</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>'Tis Honour we ſeek, and Honour we'd have,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But with your kind Grace,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>They ſearch the wrong Place,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That look for it in the Grave.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:53309:15"/>
                  <head>SCENE VI.</head>
                  <stage>James, Tyrconnel, Herbert, Powis, D'Avaux, Nugent.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>The Critical Juncture's near at hand—Now my Lords, your beſt Advice—For my part, I believe that beſides the Enemy that threatens us from the other ſide of the Water, we have a Shoal of Hereticks lurking in our Boſoms here at home— I could wiſh, with my Brother <hi>Caligula,</hi> they had All but one Neck— and then I'd make quick diſpatch with 'em—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>I am apt to believe they are all diſarm'd by This, Sir—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>That's nothing—as long as they have Arms to their Shoulders, the Rogues will be doing Miſchief—They have Plough-ſhares, and Plough-tails, and I'm afraid, too many ruſty Sithes ſtill left—Pox a' thoſe Sithes, They had like to have ruin'd me in the Weſt of <hi>England</hi>—I would not have my Men mow'd down a ſecond time by Barley-cutters—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Powis.</speaker>
                     <p>I don't believe, Sir, there's a Conſiderable Proteſtant but what is in Jayl—they tell me the Priſons are ſtov'd with 'em as thick as Loaves in a Brown Bakers Oven—I am ſure the Prieſts are abroad in every Nook and Corner under your Majeſties Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction—and the Devil's in't if a Proteſtant Thraſher eſcape 'em—I am certain they want neither Diligence nor Malice—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>I'm afraid the Rogues don't ſtarve faſt enough in Jayl—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent.</speaker>
                     <p>I know of nobody that relieves 'em—ſome of 'em were carry'd naked to the Dungeon—and tho they begg'd but the covering of an old Blanket to cover their Nakedneſs, it would not be granted—More than this, the Jaylors have order to feed 'em as if they had been ſentenc'd for ſtanding mute at their Tryals—There's nothing wanting that Catholick Zeal and Providence can do—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Are they not Chain'd?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent.</speaker>
                     <p>No, Sir, They are kept weak and low enough I'll war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ye—You may truſt 'em Male and Female together with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any danger of Procreation—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>This is ſomething to the Point, I muſt confeſs—But what muſt we do to diſperſe the main Cloud that hangs over our Heads?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:53309:15"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent.</speaker>
                     <p>May it pleaſe your Majeſty, I have read of a Story ſomewhere, I can't at preſent remember where—but I am ſure I have read it, of a certain King of the <hi>Moabites,</hi> that being afraid of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſent for one <hi>Balaam</hi> a Conjurer to curſe 'em—Is there never a <hi>Trithemius</hi> or an <hi>Agrippa</hi> of a Jeſuit, that could Summon up all the Plagues of <hi>Egypt</hi> together to help a diſheſſed Prince at a Dead Lift?—One Star of the firſt Magnitude well unhing'd by an expert Charmer, would ſqueeze the whole Camp of the Herericks into Pancake-Batter— I have heard of Showres of Wheat, and Showres of Fire that have formerly fallen at the firſt word of a devout Saint—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>I have ſaid it, and will ſay it again—there is no more truſting to Heaven in theſe caſes—for I find by my Wives laſt Miſcarriage, that Wonders from Heaven are ceaſt, and that there is a General Embargo upon Miracles in the Upper Regions—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>A deſperate Diſeaſe muſt have a deſperate Cure— Did your Majeſty ever make uſe of the Lower Regions yet—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>I believe I have ſent ſome that way in my time— but they were my Enemies, and perhaps did me more harm than good—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>We read that <hi>Ulyſſes,</hi> who was the cunningeſt Dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boots of his time, and <hi>Eneas</hi> who was the Greateſt Hector in <hi>Europe,</hi> and a Pious Prince to boot, when they were both at their Wits end, took a ſhort Fegary to <hi>Avernus,</hi> and having there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted the greateſt Politicians of that place, return'd again ſo well freighted with Council and Advice, that they got quit of all their Enemies, and dy'd i'their Beds—Your Majeſty has as ſhort a Cut to <hi>Avernus</hi> as any of thoſe Heroes here in your own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom through St. <hi>Patrick</hi>'s Hole—You may take Father <hi>Hall</hi> along with you, and be back in three days at fartheſt—There you will meet <hi>Matchiavel, Richlieu, Mazarine, Sixtus Quintus,</hi> my Lord <hi>Jefferies,</hi> and ſeveral others that will be ready to aid you with their Advice for nothing—And this I hold to be the wiſeſt Courſe your Majeſty can take, as being the only Remedy that preſerv'd thoſe Hero's, when all other means fail'd—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Would you be willing to bear me company, my Lord?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>With all my Heart—and would be contented your Majeſty ſhould leave me behind with my Preach cleaving to a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53309:16"/>Stone, as <hi>Theſeus</hi> left his Friend <hi>Pirithous,</hi> if it might be to your Majeſties Advantage—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>A very great Complement indeed, my Lord—but you know I have done ſo many ill things by your Lordſhips Advice, that I dare not truſt to the Devils Curteſie—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, you may think what you pleafe—you may do what you pleaſe—you may go to <hi>Avernus</hi> if you pleaſe—when all's done 'tis the sword muſt deſide the Quarrel—You have a brave and a numerous Army here, you have Friends in <hi>England</hi>—and if the Cock-match do but hit we are made—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Powis.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, if the Cock-match hit, 'twill ſpoil His Highneſs's Journey for <hi>Ireland</hi> I'm ſure—and I can't well deviſe how it ſhould miſs, if his Majeſty of <hi>France</hi> be not too penurious of his <hi>Leuidore's</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, my Maſter's no Snale—He knows his own buſineſs—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>And then again the Diſtinction of a King <hi>de Jure</hi> and <hi>de Facto</hi> works like Butter in a Sows Tail—One rub 'tis true will turn a Bowl from the Jack—but here are many rubs in his Highneſs's way: if he gets over 'em all—I muſt contradict your Majeſty and ſay, Miracles are not ceaſt—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>The Prince is a good Gameſter my Lord, and knows how to mend his next Caſt, tho his firſt Bowl miſcarry—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>Well—but ſuppoſe the Prince ſhould come among us—won't he be treated with?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no—my Lord, I know him too well—He'll ne're come to Compoſitions—He'll have all or none—He's too well acquainted with my Brother of <hi>France</hi> and I, to truſt the ſtrongeſt Engagements we can make him, unleſs we ſo ſecure him, that it would be the ſame thing as if we ſhould ſurrender up all into his hands—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then we muſt truſt to the Sword—They ſay Fortune aſſiſts the Daring—I am ſure ſhe never helps thoſe that lye i' the Ditch and cry God Help 'em—Men that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to dye are eaſily Maſters of other Mens Lives—Beſides there is one thing more your Majeſty does not think of—I have heard of <hi>Jacob Clements,</hi> and <hi>Ravilliac</hi>—'Tis true 'tis below Perſons of Honour to make uſe of ſuch means—but Neceſſity oft times conſtrains us to baſe Actions—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:53309:16"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>I underſtand ye, my Lord—and have been often thinking of what you ſay—but I have been cenſur'd too ſeverely already for my Brother's Death—and the buſineſs of the E. of <hi>Eſſex</hi>—and I am loath to expoſe my Memory to farther Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny—Beſides, 'tis a work of Darkneſs, not fit for preſent Conſultation—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Powis.</speaker>
                     <p>Time, Sir, prays upon your Life as well as upon Ours—Something therefore muſt be done with Expedition—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>You rather Teeze than Adviſe me my Lord—what is that you would have me to do with ſo much Expedition?—Have you got your Tools ready?—if you have, ſet 'em to work—Your <hi>Clements's</hi> and <hi>Ravilliac</hi>'s are not ſo ſoon tutor'd as you think for—Had I come ſooner to the Throne—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſaid my Maſter?—Then you had been ſooner turn'd out—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Conſequently the ſooner turn'd in again, if your Maſter's good Luck han't quite left him i'the Lurch—I fear I am come to the Ebb of his Fortune—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Powis.</speaker>
                     <p>They ſay indeed there is a Fate in all things—A Man that is born to be Hang'd ſhall never be Drown'd—and he does but row againſt the Stream that contends with Fortune—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>Fortune is many times like a <hi>Dover</hi> Poſt-horſe—ſhe'll go ſo far and no farther—I wiſh ſhe be not now in her Sullens—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>I care not a Fig for Fortune—ſhe's a Jade of all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions—ſhe's a Heathen, a Turk, a Jew, a Catholick, a Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick—ſhe waited upon <hi>Octavius Ceſar,</hi> a Pagan, to his dying Minute, but Deſerts the Moſt Chriſtian King when he has moſt need of her Aſſiſtance, and will not let him have a bit of good Luck but what he pays through the Noſe for—But let her be as Waſpiſh as ſhe will—I am perſwaded ſhe might be manacl'd with Prudence, Courage and Diligence—Sir <hi>[ſpeaking to the King]</hi> you muſt make the Streſs of your Oppoſition at the <hi>Boyne</hi>—If the Prince get that Paſs, we are all ruin'd—Had our Prieſts Faith enough to remove Mountains, half a Score of the biggeſt i'this Kingdom would be few enow to add to the Natural Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of that place—But if the Prince had a hundred Mountains to clamber, He'll get over 'em all, unleſs you oppoſe him with Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Prudence and Diligence equal to his—Sir, you muſt oppoſe the Prince and his Fortune with thoſe three Barricado's, or elſe a Ruſh for your Oppoſition—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:53309:17"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D'Avaux.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jernegoy,</hi> my Lord—you have put your Dread Sovereign upon the hardeſt Task he ever had in his Life—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, you talk of Prudence, Courage and Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence—Why thoſe my Lord, are Virtues that never grew i'this Country—The Air of this Climate has a natural Antipathy againſt 'em, and will no more endure 'em, than it will Spiders or Nightingales—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent.</speaker>
                     <p>What need Forreign Manufacture, when we have Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, Bogs and <hi>Newries</hi> of our own Growth—Poyſon all the Freſh Water i'the Country—and hang up the Proteſtants upon all the Trees i'the Road, and infect the Air with the Stench of their Carcaſſes—Strew the Graſs with Rats-bane, to kill up their Cattel—My Lords, we have Zeal without knowledge—A good Rat-catcher would Kill a thouſand of theſe Heretick Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min in a day—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lords—heres one talks of Courage and Valour, another of Poyſoning and Plaguing, and I know not what my ſelf—but no body talks of Praying to Heaven for Succeſs—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Let the Church-men do that—they have nothing elſe to do—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then my Lord <hi>D'Avaux,</hi> do you ſend into <hi>France</hi>—tell your Maſter how the caſe ſtands—adviſe him not to looſe a Hog for a Hapoth of Tar—I'll ſend into <hi>England,</hi> and do ſomething or nothing—And for you, my Lords, do you buſtle about, ride about, run about, fly about, and about and about—take the Rope as well as the Butter—if one ſlips t'other will hold—I know not what more can be ſaid, or what more can be done—</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VII.</head>
                  <stage>Hall <hi>the Jeſuit and Prieſts.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis true, 'tis a black Cloud, and gathers thicker and thicker—but I ſpake with the Queen of Heaven laſt night, and ſhe aſſur'd me ſhe would take care to diſperſe it—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I am afraid we are all out of the way; for the Queen of Heaven is but a Woman, and I fear me does not underſtand our
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53309:17"/>Buſineſs—We ſhould pray to St. <hi>Martin</hi> and the Seven Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, they underſtand M litary Affairs and Fighting—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>In truth Father <hi>Hall,</hi> we have been long enough Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Heaven without any conſiderable Succeſs—I am afraid the Saints there are all turn'd Proteſtants—And therefore I would that we ſhould now turn our Devotions downward, and ſend to <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog;</hi> there are they two, and General <hi>Belzebub</hi> would bring along an Hoſt of Infernal <hi>Huſſars</hi> able to conquer all the <hi>Cantons</hi> of <hi>Switzerland</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>How wickedly you talk Father—'tis the Interſt of the Saints to favour our Cauſe—I'm ſure there's no Religion i'the World that pays them that Reſpect which we do—All the <hi>Hereticks</hi> ſlight 'em, unleſs the School-boys for the Holy days ſake—Nay ſome are ſuch Clowns, as not to admit 'em the Title of Saint, but call 'em plain <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Matthew</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>And is there any Religion in the World that pays more reſpect to <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> and <hi>Belzebub</hi> as we do?—The <hi>Turk</hi> does not pay ſo much—Come Father, I am for driving that Nail that is moſt probable to go—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>I tell ye Father, you talk wickedly—and I am afraid our wicked Lives fight againſt us more than any thing elſe—Come, Fathers, let us come to Confeſſion a little among our ſelves—I muſt confeſs, my Father was a Cook, and dealt in Raw Fleſh; but he told me 'twas never ſo good as when it was warm, if it were not over much Roaſted—and I muſt confeſs I have lov'd, and do love, and ſo did my Mother before me, a piece of warm Fleſh—And I confeſs, I have been conniving at, and aſſiſting to help others to warm Fleſh—And half a Score Drams of your Abſolutions, Fathers, will expiate for what I have done—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I muſt confeſs I had once a very great Paſſion for a young Gentlewoman that was Marry'd, and ſhe had as great an Affection for me; but not finding an Opportunity to couzen her Jealous Husband, I ordered her to counterfeit her ſelf Sick, and to ſend for me to cure her with a Relick of a Saint that I had. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly ſhe did ſo, and fending for me, accordingly I went, and took one of my Brethren of the ſame Covent along with me, and while he was buſie with the Maid, I employ'd my time with the Sick Miſtreſs. But the Miſchief was, that being like to have been ſurpriz'd by the Husband, for haſt I left my Breeches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind; and had it not been for a Fetch that the Devil put into her
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53309:18"/>Head (I ſhall love him the better for't as long as I live) we had both been diſcover'd. But ſhe told her Husband my Breeches were the Relick of the Saint that had cur'd her, and that I had left 'em behind at her Requeſt in caſe her Fits ſhould return again, and ſo all was well. Was that any Sin, Father, to cure a Sick Lady? If it be, I muſt confeſs I have committed many a one of the ſame Nature.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Look ye, Father, here we muſt conſider the Intention of the Thing; for if the Intention were to cure the Lady, 'twas a good Intention—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>But ſhe was not Sick, but only feign'd her ſelf Sick—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>That was nothing to you—you had nothing to do to examine whether ſhe counterfeited or no—you found her Sick and you cur'd her—and ſo you fulfill'd a good Intention—And therefore Father they muſt be louder Sins than theſe that cry to Heaven and do us Miſchief.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I muſt confeſs, I made Love to another marry'd Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man—and ſhe put the Dice upon—for ſhe appointed the Night at her own Houſe, and when the time came, moſt wickedly put an Old Woman of Threeſcore and Ten to bed to me—I muſt confeſs the Old Grandame loſt nothing by it, for <hi>Jone</hi> was as good as my Lady i'the Dark—But that was not all—the next Morning ſhe ſent for all ſhe knew of her own and my Acquaintance, and expoſed me and my Female piece of wrinkled Antiquity, like <hi>Vulcan</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> to publick View; ſo that I was forc'd to forſake my Quarters, for fear of the rude <hi>Caſtigations</hi> of the Boys—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>This was a Sin, Father, for you ſuffer'd your ſelf to be gull'd by a Woman—and ſuch Sins as theſe, that is, the Diſcovery of ſuch Sins as Theſe undoes us—For it expoſes the Warts and Wenns in our Sanctity as <hi>Cham</hi> uncover'd his Father's Naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Therefore Father, to avoid the Treacheries of Women, I learnt at <hi>Rome,</hi> a notable Wary Trick they have there to make uſe of the Male Sex—And I muſt confeſs I have had a great Paſſion for ſeveral pretty Youths—And I muſt farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that I have at this time a very pretty Urchin that lyes with me every night—He has ſuch a Winning Way with him, ſuch a Charming Behaviour, and Twattles ſo like a Nightingale, that I cannot but I muſt chuck him under the Chin now and then—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:53309:18"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Take heed Father—I fear me this is that Sin which in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> they call <hi>Sodomy</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I queſtion that, <hi>Father Hall,</hi>—I am apt to believe the Ancients were miſtaken in the Signification of that word—I rather think the Inhabitants of <hi>Gomorrah</hi> made uſe of their Beaſts, and that was their Crime—and therefore it was, that in Old times they ador'd their Deities in the ſhape of Beaſts—I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe ſo many of our great Cardinals and Biſhops, Fathers of our Church, would ſet us ſuch bad Examples, if <hi>Sodomy</hi> were a Crime—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>I know indeed there was one of our Cardinals that wrote in defence of it—but I never heard of any that ever wrote in behalf of Adultery—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>'Tis certain Father, that He who commits one Sin, ſins leſs than he that commits two at a time—Now he that commits <hi>Adultery,</hi> runs himſelf into Prodigality and Expence upon his Beloved, and at the ſame time invades his Neighbours Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty—but a ſmooth Chinn'd Youth preſerves a Man from the Guilt of both thoſe Crimes—and who would go to a Crown Ordinary, when he may pleaſe his Appetite better for Six pence?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis true indeed, we are born Fleſh and Blood, and tho our Church forbids us to Marry, Nature will have its Courſe—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>If Men did not ſometimes commit Errors, there would be no need of Repentance—That's the Remedy which we are order'd to make uſe of for the attoning of Heaven in caſes of Neceſſity and Diſtreſs—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>Therefore Fathers, as we have been all great Sinners, I would have ye apply your ſelves to this Remedy—and make fair Weather with Heaven till the Storm be over—Our Affairs are now in a tickliſh Condition—Then it will be time enough to break your Vows and Contracts with Heaven, when y'are at eaſe and in Proſperity—He that vow'd a Wax Candle to the Holy Virgin as big as the Main Maſt, when he was in danger to be caſt away, thought her not worth one of Twelve to the Pound, when he was got ſafe a Shore—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Now, Father, you make me Scratch where it does not itch—But do you think, Father, there is any ſuch danger of the Prince of <hi>Orange?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:53309:19"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>I know not what to think on't Fathers—but exerciſe your <hi>Cats a Nine Tails</hi>—let every Man be a Whipping <hi>Tom</hi> to his own Fleſh—Repentance you know ſav'd <hi>Nineveh</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Now would the whole Univerſe were turn'd Topſie Turvy, and <hi>Satan</hi> ſole Lord of the Upper Regions—Sure <hi>Satan</hi> would not let the Cauſe of his Servants ſuffer—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>You wiſh well, Father—but let us be whoſe Servants we will—I do not find that either Heaven or Hell takes any care of us—and for my part, of all Repentances I don't like this <hi>Cat a Nine Tail Repentance</hi>—This nointing a Mans Back with Sacred Oyl of <hi>Whipcord</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>'Tis no more than what the Proverb ſays—<hi>Sweet Meat muſt have Sowre Sauce</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Then give me leave to wiſh in my turn—that our Sowre Sauce may bring us Sweet Meat at length—When I Whip my ſelf upon my own Accompt, I lay it on ſo gently, that if I ſhould hit a Louſe I ſhould do it no hurt—but this Whipping upon a National Accompt, I d ead the thoughts of it—It makes my Back ſore before I touch it—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis a National Accompt indeed, Fathers—for if we looſe this place, we looſe all our Hopes in this World—and for the other, I am ſure neither you nor I think of it—You looſe the Fruits of all your Maſſacres and Rebellions—We looſe the Fruits of all our Plots and Conſpiracies—A <hi>Jeſuit</hi> hitherto ſo Famous for his Politicks, will be lookt upon no better than a Jakes Farmer—His <hi>Holineſs</hi> minds nothing but to keep the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King</hi> out of <hi>Italy</hi>—and the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King</hi> himſelf will have both his Hands too full to do us any good—Who would not Whip himſelf, as you may ſuppoſe <hi>Jehu</hi> Whipt his Horſes, rather than this ſhall come to paſs!—The way to Laſh our Enemies is to Whip our ſelves—Luſtily, Floggingly, Stoutly, Robuſtiouſly, Vigorouſly—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Truly, Father, I fear the Mercy of my Hand—I ſhould hardly torment my ſelf at ſuch a Rate, to ſave <hi>Rome</hi> from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſackt again by the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals</hi>—Can you think of no other, but this <hi>Drive on Carman</hi> way to ſave this poor <hi>Iſland?</hi>—Well—I have it now—and I hope my Ingenuity will ſecure my Shoulders—Come Fathers, come along with me—</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="scene">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:53309:19"/>
                  <head>ACT. II. <hi>Scene</hi> 8.</head>
                  <stage>Tyrconnel, <hi>Primate, Nugent,</hi> Hall <hi>and Prieſts.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                     <p>GOod morrow, Fathers—what News brings you here ſo early?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>We have been up, my Lord all Night, at our Devotions, and ſomething Heaven has inform'd us of, for publick good.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, we humbly conceive, here has been a very great neglect—for numbers of Men ſignifie little without a Bleſſing from above.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prim.</speaker>
                     <p>Have you brought thoſe <hi>Bleſſings</hi> along with <hi>you,</hi> Fathers?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>No, my Lord—but we wonder they have not bin ſent for all this while, from the <hi>Fountain</hi> where they are to be had upon Earth—We have heard of ſeveral Princes, that have been preſented with Conſecrated Swords, and Belts, and Hats of great value by St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor; by virtue of which they have wrought Miracles, and won mighty Victories, to the unſpeakable Propagation of the <hi>Holy-Church;</hi> but we hear of none of theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated Swords that have been ſent to our Soveraign, or ſo much as deſired in his behalf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I ſhould rather adviſe, that his Holineſs might be ſent to for a hundred thouſand Conſecrated <hi>Aſſes Jaw-Bones</hi>—for by that means might every one of our Souldiers prove a <hi>Sampſon</hi>—Or elſe I would have his Holineſs to ſend us St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Sword—(for if he has his Keys, there is no doubt, but he has his Sword too)—for then would I undertake, that if our Souldiers ſhould but touch their Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons with that Sword, they would receive a particular Virtue from it, as a Million of <hi>Needles</hi> from the touch of one <hi>Load-ſtone;</hi> and then would every ſingle Souldier kill a thouſand Hereticks.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                     <p>I do not underſtand, Fathers, any need we have of recurring to ſuch extraordinary Miracles.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>No, my Lord, if all Men, had your Lordſhips Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but the fears of Men, and cauſes of their Fears, are as various as their Faces—They are all <hi>Godfrey of Bullens,</hi> till they ſee their Enemies—but then this thing frights 'em, and t'other thing ſcares 'em—and then run, he that can run faſteſt.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Why therefore 'tis, <hi>Fathers,</hi> that while we are a going to fight, you muſt pray for the Succeſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas! my Lord, we are Men of Frailty as well as others,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53309:20"/>and therefore I have always obſerved, that one <hi>Pious Fraud</hi> is worth a hundred <hi>Pious Ave-Maries</hi>—Of thoſe your Lordſhip knows that we have many—and never did the Difficulties of our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mother the Church, more than now, require the practice of them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Primate.</speaker>
                     <p>For thoſe things, take your own Courſes, Fathers, you know the Duties of your Functions—and have my Power for your aſſiſtance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, pray ſend for half a ſcore Officers and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers— you ſhall then ſee what Courſe we intend to take.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Officers and Souldiers to them.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen, you are ſent for hither, to let you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that you are now to fight for your Holy Mother the Church, your King, and your Country.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Officer.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By my ſhoul, Fathers, we know all this—but Fathers, however Lifes ſhweet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Officer.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>And then again, Fathers, 'tis well known, that we <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Iriſh,</hi> have a ſtrange <hi>Antipathy</hi> againſt Farting—but the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> great Guns keep ſuch a Bouncing and Roaring, as if all the Winds in the <hi>Compaſh</hi> were in their Breeſhes, and they ſpit Fire, and ſhit Lead and Iron at ſuch a rate, that we muſt confeſh, they make a great fear upon us ſhometimes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>But you are Souldiers and Men of Honour—and ſuch have always held it better to dye bravely in the Field, than to live in Slavery, without your Laws, your Eſtates and Religion. And who would not rather chooſe to dye a Martyr, and go immediately to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, than live Bog-trotting and ſtealing of Cows upon this miſerable Earth?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Officer.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>But I have been a leud Liver all my Life, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſh, and you tell us ſo often of a <hi>Damnaſhion</hi> to come—that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times it makes me rather ſhooſe to live a little longer, than to be poſhted out of this World I know not whither.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>As for that, Gentlemen, you ſhall have Pardons in your Pockets, under the Hands and Seals of his Holineſs, for all the ſins that ever you Committed, of what nature ſoever—ſo that all who are ſlain, ſhall go to Heaven forthwith, before a Cat can lick her Ear—Nay, there ſhall be a Note taken of their Names, and they ſhall all be Canoniz'd too—There they ſhall fit all the day long, and eat <hi>Ambroſia,</hi> and drink <hi>Nectar,</hi> which are as far beyond <hi>Bonny Clapper</hi> and <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſquebagh,</hi> as <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſquebagh</hi> and <hi>Bonni Clapper,</hi> are
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53309:20"/>beyond dead ſmall <hi>Beer</hi> and <hi>Poor John.</hi> There they ſhall be attended with lovely young Girls with golden Waſtcoats, and azure Petti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coats, to play with, and ſing 'em aſteep. There they ſhall ſit with Crowns upon their Heads, commanding every one a Province as big as all <hi>Ireland.</hi> Theſe are the Rewards of thoſe that are ſlain in the defence of the Holy Shorches Cauſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4. <hi>Officer.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>But ſuppoſe our Breeſhes are rifl'd, and our Pardons taken out of our Pockets.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>That will ſignifie nothing—St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſhall let you in for all that—you will be known by your very Deaths Wounds—Why, look ye Dear Joys, in whom do you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Officer.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>We believe in the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> and St. <hi>Pautrick.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>And don't you believe the Cauſe of the holy Mother the Church, to be a good Cauſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Officer.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Yeſh, by my ſhoule do we.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Why, then y'are worſe than Turks, if ye don't fight to the laſt gaſp in a good Cauſe.—For the Turks believe they never ſhall dye till their time appointed be come—and that has made 'em ſo victorious—if your time be come, it matters not whether you be ſlain by a Bullet, or a fall down Stairs in your <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſquebah</hi>—if your time be not come, all the Bullets in the Kingdom can never touch ye.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Officer.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By my <hi>ſhoule,</hi> Father, if the whole Army were as well ſhatisfied as we, they would fight like ſo many Lyons for their Preys—what ſay you, Dear Joys?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>We ſay as you ſay,—and we ſay as the Fathers ſay,—and the Fathers have made great ſhatisfaſſions upon us, by St. <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick.</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hall.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſpeak like noble Champions of the Church—go then, and inculcate theſe things into the minds of your Fellow <hi>Dear-Joys,</hi> and we'll be ſure to be with you every day, to confirm you in your Reſolutions.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt <hi>Officers and Souldiers.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Look ye, my Lord, this is the only way to make theſe People fight—For if the conſiderations of future Beatitude, ſo ſenſual as we make it, won't do, nothing elſe I am ſure will do it. And therefore, my Lord, you ſee we have made it as ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual as that of <hi>Mahomets.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Primate.</speaker>
                     <p>I like your way very well, Fathers; therefore come
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53309:21"/>to me, and I'le let ye have Pardons by the <hi>Buſhel</hi>—you may get what you can from the Commanders—but let the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Souldiers have 'em for nothing—Braſs Money ſignifies little at <hi>Rome.</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent.</speaker>
                     <p>There is one way more, we have forgot, which is the Turkiſh way, to intoxicate their Souldiers with <hi>Opium,</hi> before they engage—for ſince the moſt Chriſtian King makes uſe of the Turkiſh Force, we may as well make uſe of the Turkiſh Policy— Put <hi>Opium</hi> in their Snuſh, and they ruſh into Battel, and ſight for a time, like Game-Cocks—ſo that the Enemy will never be able to withſtand their Lubberly Multitude.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>This way, or that way, or any way, ſo we can but get 'em to ſtand the Bruſhes they are like to endure—And therefore Fathers, try the force of your Divinity-Magick.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>We'll do all that lyes in our Power, you may be ſure, my Lord.—
<q>
                           <l>
                              <hi>'Twas we that made 'em formerly rebell,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And now we hope to make 'em fight as well,</hi>
                           </l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="scene">
                  <head>ACT. II. <hi>Scene</hi> 9.</head>
                  <stage>Lauzune, Lutterel, Tyrconnel.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzune.</speaker>
                     <p>WOuld you not have the King, Sir, keep his Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with my Maſter:—You know, that when your ſelf, together with the Lord Mayor and Aldermen Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſt him about this Buſineſs, in hopes that he would ſtill conſide in you and them to govern <hi>Dublin,</hi> the King made anſwer, that he had paſt his Word to his Brother <hi>Lewis,</hi> that I ſhould have the Government of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and therefore could not recede from it.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I am as yet chief Governour of this Kingdom un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my Maſter, King <hi>James,</hi> and believe the Town to be already in ſafe hands—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lutt.</speaker>
                     <p>What Contracts our Maſter made when he was abroad un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Maſters Power, are invalid in his own Dominions—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzun.</speaker>
                     <p>Is it ſo? Then 'tis time for me to return home again with my Maſters aſſiſtance—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Of what?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzun.</speaker>
                     <p>Of five thouſand old beaten Souldiers.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>For which you had the ſame Number of new raiſed Men, which a Winters Diſcipline, would ſoon make as fit for ſervice, as the beſt Men in your Maſters Army.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:53309:21"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzun.</speaker>
                     <p>Did not my Maſter furniſh you with Wine, Frute, Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, Hops, Tobacco, and other Commodities?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>And did not you carry off our Butter, Cheeſe, Wool, Raw Hides and Tallow; and did not the King releaſe ſeven pound ten ſhillings upon every Tun of your Wine?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzun.</speaker>
                     <p>That's nothing to the purpoſe—if you quarrel with my Maſter—you'll loſe the beſt Card in your Pack — and therefore I demand the Keys of the City and Caſtle, as by agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between my Maſter and yours.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſo faſt, Sir,—who's King in <hi>Ireland,</hi> your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or ours?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzune.</speaker>
                     <p>I know no King in <hi>Ireland,</hi> but my Maſter K. <hi>Lewis,</hi> and therefore once more in his Name I demand the Keys of the Caſtle and City.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lutt.</speaker>
                     <p>One would think the Keys of the City ſhould ſerve your turn—there's room enough to quarter your handful of men—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzun.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, My Maſter does not uſe to be contented with Cities, unleſs he may have the Citadels that command 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Then it ſeems your Maſter intends to make a Conqueſt of this Kingdom,—marry ſo far as hitherto, it comes eaſie enough to him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzun.</speaker>
                     <p>I know not what my Maſter intends to do—I am nor of his Council—but this I am ſure of, that private Men never lend great Sums, but upon good Security.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Thus Prodigal Heirs, when hungry, ſell their Birth-Rights for a Meſs of Porridge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> K. J.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K. J.</speaker>
                     <p>Why ſo much colour in your faces here, my Lords?— This is no time for Heats and Quarrels.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lutt.</speaker>
                     <p>Here's General <hi>Lauzune,</hi> Sir, demands the Keys of your City and Caſtle of <hi>Dublin</hi>—I know not how I have trangreſs'd in my ſidelity to your Majeſty, but that I may be ſtill entruſted with them as well as He; Does your Majeſty intend the <hi>French</hi> ſhall make a <hi>Palatinate</hi> of <hi>Ireland?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Peace, <hi>Lutterel,</hi>—you are too hot.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lutt.</speaker>
                     <p>Would it not vex, Sir, any Man of Mettle to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graded from his Honour, to oblige an <hi>Alien?</hi>—Give him the reſt too, and ſave nothing for your ſelf, but empty Name.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Intreague of State, above thy reach, and private Contract between my Brother <hi>Lewis</hi> and my ſelf, command thy ſwift Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:53309:22"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lutt.</speaker>
                     <p>Then take your Keys, Sir, and diſpoſe of 'em at your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; it ſhall never be ſaid that my hand ever did ſo poor an Act— however give a loſer leave to ſpeak—Had you kept your word but half ſo well with your <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects, as you do with the <hi>French,</hi> you had never been reduc'd to this.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>[Exit</hi> Lutt.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>James</hi> to <hi>Lauzune.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, Loſers will ſometimes be in paſſion, tho' they loſe their money never ſo fairly—He's honeſt, tho' forgetful of his Duty at this time—Beſides Severity would be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable at ſuch a Juncture as this—'Tis ſufficient for you that I have kept my Promiſe with your Maſter—You ſee the Keys are yours, you may now go take poſſeſſion when you pleaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Excunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="scene">
                  <head>ACT. II. <hi>Scene</hi> 10.</head>
                  <stage>Lauzune, <hi>Solus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>BEgar me dank de King for noting—He delivre me de Key of dis Gran Citee, and of de Chaſtel dat command it, begar, becauſe he know no vich vay to elp imſelf—begar me Maitre tank a de King vor noting—begar he dare as vel tack a de Bear a by de toot, as diſoblige a mee Maitre—Begar mee Maitre be de gran King of de varle—and begar me bee de gran Prince of <hi>Irlanda</hi>—begar me make a de King ſubmeet a to mee, mee varrant him—mee a got de poſſeſſion of de gran Citee of <hi>Dubleen,</hi> and of de Caſtel, and mee keep a dem bor begar, or if dey voree a mee to run a de way—mee run a de way by de light of 'em—begar me ſet all on de veere, mee burn, burn, kill, kill, and make all as plain as my nail—but firſt mee plundra all de Hereteeks, and de Papiſts boat—mee make up mee bundla mee garant mee.—
<q>
                        <l>Foutre Diable of de Gran Prince of <hi>Irlanda,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>That can't lick his fingra, having all at commanda.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:53309:22"/>
               <head>ACT III.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Scene</hi> 1.</head>
                  <stage>King, Tyrconnel, Hamilton, Primate, Nugent, Mac Gillicuddy, Butler, Talbot.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <p>MY Lords, I make no queſtion but you hear the News of the P. of <hi>Orange</hi>'s being Landed, and my Intelligence from <hi>England,</hi> confirms the number of his well provided Forces— He comes with all the Preparations of a Great, a Prudent, and a wary Captain—And now he's come, I know he will not trifle time away—In the mean time all's quiet in <hi>England</hi>— not a Mouſe ſtins in my behalf, and that perplexes me— I wiſh I were well rid of this unwelcome Gueſt—but ugly fears poſſeſs me.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                     <p>However ſhew 'em not, Great Sir, that will diſhearten all the reſt.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>No, My Lord, not ſo neither; I'le have one bruſh for't, you may be ſure, what e're comes on't—But you know, my Lord, we muſt be forc'd to leave <hi>Dublin</hi> but thinly mann'd behind us—and 'tis a fowl Neſt of Hereticks—I wiſh they had bin all tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported long ago.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                     <p>You know, Sir, that was debated in Council at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning—But then it was found, that all the <hi>Butchers, Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Bakers, Clothiers, Weavers, Taylors, Shoo-makers, Hat-makers, Smiths, Carpenters,</hi> and other <hi>Artizans</hi> were Hereticks, ſo that had they bin remov'd, your Souldiers could have had neither Meat, Bread, nor Drink, nor Cloaths to wear, nor Carts to carry their Proviſion and Ammunition into the Field; nor would your Majeſty have had a Mint and Workmen to Coyn your Braſs and Copper.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nugent.</speaker>
                     <p>However, Sir, there is Order taken to ſecure the Hereticks ſafe enough—Your own Example in <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s time, has taught us to confine 'em all with in the Churches, Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals and Jayls of the City, 'till the Buſineſs be well over; and then you may make Bonfires of 'em for your Victories.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Well then, that care's over—But how ſtands the Army affected for fighting? are they in the ſame brave humour they were in, when I laſt took a view of 'em.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                     <p>I think ſo, Sir, they ſhow the ſame Symptoms of Valour
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53309:23"/>as ever, they Drink as hard, Swear as hard, toſs about your Health as faſt, Bounce, and Rant, and Swagger as loud as ever, and quarrel with one another as much as e're they did— and why they ſhould not fight the Enemy as Boldly and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly as they Duel one another, I know not—This I dare ſay, they will either fight or run away; but that's left to their Diſcretion—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, but to come more cloſe to the Buſineſs— you ſee the <hi>Newry</hi>'s loſt, and you all agree that if we loſe <hi>Ardee,</hi> the <hi>Boyne</hi> is the next Paſs to be defended—ſo that it looks like ſtopping one Torrent by another.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hamilton.</speaker>
                     <p>Goads Bread, and I'le undertake to hold the Enemy play there this whole Summer—or I'le give him leave to make a whiſtle o' my Tayl—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Bravely ſaid, <hi>Hamilton</hi>—but is the River forda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble?—for if it be.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ham.</speaker>
                     <p>What if it be? I'le have it undermin'd, and blow 'em up, if they offer to ſet foot in the water—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Greatly ſaid again, <hi>Hamilton</hi>—But I have heard that Old Prince <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> had ſuch a Trick of paſſing Rivers, that Duke <hi>d'Alva</hi> put the Queſtion, whether his Army had wings or no—Now ſuppoſe our Enemies ſhould have ſuch a knack.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ham.</speaker>
                     <p>Bread a Goad, Sir, I have men under my Command, that will kill a Sparrow or a Tit-Mouſe flying, much more a Horſe or a Man; if they do not fly in the Night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>But what if they do—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ham.</speaker>
                     <p>What if they do? Why then bread a Goad, Sir, I have a way to prevent that too, by driving ſtakes into the ground, all along this ſide of the River, for many Miles together, with their upper ends as ſharp as Needles—ſo that when they come to light, they muſt of neceſſity ſpit themſelves with their own weight— A General without Stratagems, is like a Mountebank without his Receipts.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>James.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, my Lords, if we can but ſtop him ten days, I make no queſtion but to ſee an Alteration of the Weather in our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs—for I have certain intelligence from Our Brother of <hi>France,</hi> that he has ſo ordered it in <hi>England,</hi> that the Prince's Fleet will not fight, but leave the <hi>Dutch</hi> in the <hi>Lurch,</hi> if they preſume an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement—ſo that the <hi>French</hi> being Maſters of the Sea, we ſhall have what Aſſiſtance we deſire here, beſides a numerous Invaſion of <hi>England</hi> it ſelf, to joyn with our Friends in that Kingdom—
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53309:23"/>My Brother of <hi>France</hi> well knows that if I fall, his Univerſal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy muſt ſink—My Lords, theſe are my hopes, and theſe my Fears—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Talbot.</speaker>
                     <p>Does your great Game, dear Sir, depend upon a ten days ſtop—that's too too mean, to beg of <hi>hoary</hi> Time— We'll make it <hi>Agamemnon</hi>'s Toyl to gain the <hi>Boyne</hi>—I ſcorn to fly—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ham.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſo do I—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gillicuddy.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſo do I—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Butler.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſo do I—Unleſs the Souldiers turn their backs and Flie—For 'twas never my ambition to fight whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies alone.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter an Iriſh Souldier, ſtaring and Breathleſs.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                     <p>How now, Fellow-Souldier—what News?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                     <p>By my Shoule, Dear Joy, very bad—I waſh one of thoſe that was ſet to guard the <hi>Paſh,</hi> within four miles of the <hi>Newry;</hi> and there we had news that the <hi>Danes</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> were advanced as far as the <hi>Newry</hi>—preſently they ſent us word, that if we burnt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more Houſes, they would give no quarter either to <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi>—By and by we ſaw a Party of them appear at a diſtance— and by St. <hi>Pautrick,</hi> they look'd all like your <hi>Sharazens,</hi> with turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pike Beards on each ſide their Mouths, as ſharp as Boars Tuſhes— which made ſuch a great fear upon us, that we preſently quitted the Paſh, and made haſte to <hi>Ardee,</hi> my <hi>Dear Joy</hi>—Had your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip bin there, my <hi>Dear Joy,</hi> you would have done the ſhame, by my Shoule—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Could you obſerve their Number?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                     <p>By my ſhoule, <hi>dear Joy,</hi> I believe there might be about thirty Thouſand—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>How! thirty Thouſand, Man!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                     <p>By my ſhoule, they made ſo great fear upon me, that I have hardly yet recovered my ſelf—By St. <hi>Pautrick,</hi> I am ſhure there was great many more than four hundred—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, is this all you can ſay?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                     <p>Yeſh, by my ſhoule—and I think enough too—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K. J.</speaker>
                     <p>A very good beginning, by my Troth—This is juſt Hey, paſs and be gone—If the Concluſion be no better—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ham.</speaker>
                     <p>You are not, Sir, to judge of all the reſt, by the Cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of one Raſcallion Slave—Let 'em enjoy a Trivial Paſs or two—
<q>
                           <l>And let them all their Numerous Forces joyn,</l>
                           <l>There's nothing won, till they have won the <hi>Boyn.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:53309:24"/>
                  <head>ACT III. <hi>Scene</hi> 2. <hi>Repreſenting a Sutler's Tent.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Three Iriſh Captains,</hi> 3 <hi>Iriſh Lieutenants,</hi> 3 <hi>Iriſh Enſigns, Sutler.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Capt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Well—<hi>Dear Joys,</hi> what ſhall we drink this Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>E'en what you pleaſe, Captain—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Capt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Hey, <hi>Sutler,</hi>—what's the beſt Liquor by St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sutler.</speaker>
                     <p>All's beſt, my <hi>dear Joys,—Claret, White-Wine, Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſquebagh,</hi>—which you like beſt—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Capt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Then bring us half a dozen Bottles of <hi>Claret</hi>—better we drink it, than the <hi>Hereticks</hi> have it—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[They all drink three or four Healths about, and then ceaſe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Capt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Well—my <hi>dear Joys,</hi> have ye been at the King's Tent this Morning? How goe Squares—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Capt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Yeſh, I was at the King's Tent—There was all in deep Conſiderations and Conſultations—not a great Officer to be ſpoken with; and ſo I left 'em by St. <hi>Pautrick</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Capt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>What think you on't, Captain—how does the Pulſe of your Heart beat?—For by my ſhoule, the Prince will make a quick puſh fort—he encamps in the Plains of <hi>Dundalk</hi> this Night— and then by my ſhoule, he will be with us to Morrow—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Capt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By my ſhoule, my Heart beats but faintly—The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil tauke me now, if I do love theſe <hi>French</hi> Men—They begin to Tyranniſe over us already—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Lieutenant.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By St. <hi>Pautrick,</hi> I had like to have run my skein— through a <hi>French</hi> Captain's Guts but t'other Night, for calling me <hi>Eriſh Teague</hi>—however, I flung a Glaſs of Wine in his Faſh— and had we not been parted, I had let the Sun through his Body—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Lieutenant.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By my ſhoule, I will fight for his Majeſty, for my Reliſhions, and for the Holy Fathers the Preiſtſhs, but I will not fight for the <hi>French</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Lieutenant.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By St. <hi>Pautrick,</hi> a Son of a ten thouſand Fathers of a <hi>French</hi> Man, told me to my <hi>Faſh</hi> t'other day, that he knew no King in <hi>Ireland,</hi> but King <hi>Lewis</hi>—I could ha' kickt him to Hell, had I thought him worth the Devils acceptanſh—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Capt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Why this, by my ſhoule, it is, <hi>dear Joys,</hi> that makes the Pulſe of my Heart beat ſo faintly—By St. <hi>Pautrick,</hi> I am
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:53309:24"/>in a quandary whether I ſhall fight or run for it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Enſign.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By my ſhoule, <hi>dear Joy,</hi> if I ſee you run, I'le follow with the Colours—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Enſign.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By my ſhoule, Captain, I think it nonſenſe to fight for the <hi>French</hi> againſt his Majeſty—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Captain.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By St. <hi>Pautrick,</hi> I think we ſhall be all of one mind by and by—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Enſign.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I don't know, noble Captain, that ever we true born <hi>Iriſh,</hi> ever diſagree'd among our ſelves in theſe points—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Capt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Suppoſe we ſhould get the day, and the <hi>French</hi> ſhould come in and overrun our Wives and Foſter Siſters,—what ſhould we get by that?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Lieutenant.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>'Tis true, I could be as cruel as another to another, but not to my ſelf—but he's cruel to himſelf, that fights for him that intends him a miſchief—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Capt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>And therefore 'tis, that I like the way of Maſſacring <hi>Hereticks,</hi> much better than fighting with <hi>Hereticks</hi>—'Tis a more Compendious way, and done with leſs trouble—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Capt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Why then, <hi>dear Joy,</hi> what think ye of make Petitions to his Majeſty, that the buſineſs may be decided by moſt at three throws, I have a lucky hand at flinging ſometimes—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Enſign.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Or ſuppoſe you ſhould loſe—the difference would be determined without Bloodſhed—and the Chance of Fortune the ſame—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Enſign.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Or, let three to three, ſet foot to foot, and they that fall firſt, loſe all—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Cap.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>No, Enſign—there would be no Chance in that—for then the <hi>Danes</hi> or the <hi>Dutch</hi> would be ſure to win—But what need all this diſpute?—We are ſafe as yet—there's a Wall of Water between us; nor any thing but their Cannons can hurt us—and I hope that none of us were ever ſo Curſt in our Mothers Bellies, to be killed with a Cannon Bullet upon dry Land—Hark—by St. <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick</hi> the Drums are in an Uproar—There's Miſchief at hand by Creeſh—Enſign look out, and ſee what's the matter—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enſign <hi>goes out and returns.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Enſign.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>The Enemy's in view—and we are all Commanded to our Poſts—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Capt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Nay then, if they are ſo valiant, as to fight with two the moſt miſchievous of all the four Elements at once, let every man do as God and St. <hi>Pautrick</hi> direct him—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:53309:25"/>
                  <head>ACT III. <hi>Scene</hi> 3.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Meſſenger, D. of</hi> Berwick, Sarsfield.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>PArdon, great Sir, the Tydings which I bring, Of a loſt Kingdom, and a vanquiſh'd King.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. of B.</speaker>
                     <p>Speak out the dreaded Truth—I fear my Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtill proves unſucceſsful—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Juſt as you ſay, Sir,—Free Paſſage o're the <hi>Boyn</hi> the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies has gain'd—Your Royal Father's Forces routed and diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed—and he himſelf haſting once more to reimbark for <hi>France</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsfield.</speaker>
                     <p>Curſe o' my Stars, that I muſt be detach'd that day— I would have wreſted Victory out of Heretick Fortunes hands—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. of B.</speaker>
                     <p>Wert thou in the Engagement, Friend?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I was one of your Royal Father's Guard that day—and being poſted where he ſtood, beheld the whole Action—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. of B.</speaker>
                     <p>Then give us the beſt acount of it thou canſt—For in his Letter to me, my Father only tells me, I muſt ſhift for my ſelf—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>upon the 30th. of <hi>June,</hi> the Enemy encamped within ſight of us, the River <hi>Boyn</hi> being between Us and Them—but it ſeems the <hi>P.</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi> did not think fit to Enterpriſe any thing that day, in regard the Body of the Infantry and Artillery did not come up till late—however we could diſcover him riding to and fro' to view the Poſture of our Army, and judg'd it was he, by the Attendance that hover'd about him, which made us fire with two Pieces of ſix pound Ball among the Thickeſt—but as if all our Bullets had been <hi>Huguenots,</hi> not one would touch him, but one that only kiſſed the top of his ſhoulder, and whiſpered him in the Ear, as if For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune had only ſent to welcome him to the <hi>Boyn,</hi> and encourage him the more to our Ruine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsfield.</speaker>
                     <p>Damn'd Traytor of a ſix Pounder—No wonder we go thus to rack, when our Bullets won't do their Office—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>The next day, we were firſt attack'd by a great Body of the Enemy, under Count <hi>Schomberg,</hi> who having paſs'd the River near to <hi>Slane,</hi> forc'd his way through eight hundred Dragoons that guarded the Ford, and being reinforc'd with freſh Succours, after a ſmall reſiſtance, routed all that oppoſed him, and drave them as far as <hi>Duleek.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsf.</speaker>
                     <p>That word <hi>ſmall reſiſtance</hi> makes me mad—why <hi>ſmall reſiſtance,</hi> i'the Devils Name?—<hi>Small Reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>ſmall Beer,</hi>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:53309:25"/>are much at one—May they be accurſt, and never taſte ſtrong Drink more, for their <hi>ſmall-Beer</hi> Fighting—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>On the other ſide, the <hi>Danes</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> in a great Body, took the ſtream like ſo many <hi>ſhag Spaniels</hi>—and fighting up to the middle in the Water, beat off our Men, and gaining the Land, rout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all before 'em—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsf.</speaker>
                     <p>The Devil take 'em for a Company of Sons of Water-Dogs—Where was <hi>Lauzune</hi> all this while?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, Sir, at the ſame time the <hi>P.</hi> of <hi>O.</hi> paſſing the River at the head of a great Body of Horſe, attacked <hi>Lauzune</hi> with a Bravery to be extold, tho' in an Enemy, and forc'd him to give way; and at length to retire, finding himſelf abandon'd by the Foot—'Tis true, he retreated in good Order, after the loſs of General <hi>Hamilton</hi> taken Priſoner—but the reſt diſperſt and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſome ran one way, ſome another—leaving all our Baggage and eight Pieces of Cannon as a Pray to the Victors—All that prov'd lucky to us in this Battel, was this, that Duke <hi>Schom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> was ſlain with a Carbine-ſhot, at the head of his Men, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to obſerve <hi>Lauzune</hi>'s motions—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. of B.</speaker>
                     <p>Where was my Royal Father all this while?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>He ſtood upon a riſing ground i' the Rear, out of harms way, where with Tears in his Eyes for a while he beheld the bad Condition of his Affairs—till at length my Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> crying out with a deſpairing Voice, <hi>Sauvez le Roy,</hi>—and his Majeſty, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Army all in diſorder, took care to ſave himſelf, and fled with all ſpeed to <hi>Dublin</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. of B.</speaker>
                     <p>What was our loſs?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>The loſs of the whole Kingdom, an't like your Grace—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. of B.</speaker>
                     <p>I mean what our particular loſs?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>About fifteen hundred ſlain, and a great number of Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners—I forgot to tell you, Sir, there was one whole Regiment ran away, without ſo much as taking up their Arms from the ground where they had Regimentally laid 'em—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsf.</speaker>
                     <p>Thoſe were Sparks of <hi>Venus,</hi> I'le warrant ye, Sir—ſuch as had rather fight in a Brothel-Houſe than in a pitch'd Field— a bleſſed ſtory—Now the Devil take me, if all theſe Fellows do not deſerve to be fairly hang'd out of the way, that we may have no more of the breed of 'em—Oh—Yonder I ſee ſome of the Raſcals coming hither for ſhelter—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>[The Scene diſcovers a great number of Fugitives running to</hi> Sarsfield<hi>'s Body for ſecurity.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:53309:26"/>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>half a ſcore duſty</hi> Teagues.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsf.</speaker>
                     <p>Scoundrels where have you left your Arms?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Souldier.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By my ſhoule, <hi>dear Joy,</hi> we have left 'em behind us—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By my ſhoule, <hi>dear Joy,</hi> we made great fire upon the Enemies, till they came ſo near us, that we were afraid they would have taken us Priſoners, by St. <hi>Pautrick</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By Creeſh, <hi>dear Joy,</hi> I club'd out the Brains of no leſs than ſeven Hereticks at one time—yeſh marry did I—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsf.</speaker>
                     <p>I warrant they were dead before—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Yeſh indeed were they, <hi>dear Joy,</hi>—but they made ſuch fear upon me as they lay, that I reſolv'd to kill 'em again—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By <hi>Creeſh</hi> now, 'twas in my Thoughts to have fought like a Devil—but the Rogues ſent us word, that if we did, they would give us no Quarter—and ſo when all run, I run for good Company—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsf.</speaker>
                     <p>The Deaths of drown'd Kittens in a Horſe-Pond, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ye all—What encouragement has a Man of Courage to entruſt himſelf with ſuch Vermin—l'de truſt my ſelf as ſoon in a Hare-Warren, againſt a Heard of Wolves—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>5. <hi>Souldier.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By my ſhoule, <hi>dear Joy,</hi> you do us wrong, we did as much as Men could do—but we met with Men that were more than Men—You know, <hi>dear Joy,</hi> it is a hard matter to row againſt the Stream—but theſe Men fought againſt the Stream, and yet beat us—They ſtood i'th' Water like Stakes,— and fir'd ſo faſt out of the Water upon us, that we could not ſtand upon the dry Land—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. of B.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, Colonel, there's no help for no Remedy— 'Tis my Royal Father's Misfortune to work with bad Tools—and the beſt Artiſt in the World can never make a Silk Purſe of a Sows Ear.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsfield.</speaker>
                     <p>However there's Life in a Muſcle ſtill—the <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> have not done all their Work yet—we have ſomething ſtill left, that will hold 'em play for ſome time—and if we can but get freſh Succours from <hi>France,</hi> we may be able to turn the Scales—or elſe at leaſt to make an honourable Compoſition for our ſelves.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:53309:26"/>
                  <head>ACT III. <hi>Scene</hi> 4.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>King</hi> J. Tyrconnel, Herbert, <hi>Mayor of</hi> Dublin, <hi>and others.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K. J.</speaker>
                     <p>TO Day a Man, to Morrow a Mouſe—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>I muſt confeſs, I was in hopes I might have had a Mace carryed before me, as well as my Capital Enemy <hi>Jef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feries</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Loſe all in one day, without hopes of ever having a Back Game to play! What will the World think of us?— They'l ſay, ſurely we were either very Improvident, or very Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident Gameſters, to hazard all at one Throw—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K. J.</speaker>
                     <p>I muſt confeſs, I long miſtruſted the Iſſue of this day, and therfore it was, that I ſent away <hi>Trant,</hi> to prepare Ships for my return into <hi>France</hi> before the Fight—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twas ill foreboded, an't pleaſe your Majeſty—but by this you have acquired the Honour of being the greateſt Prince in the World, happy in your Misfortunes, to be both a King, a Prieſt, and a Prophet; which is more than your Brother <hi>Lewis</hi> can pretend to—A King without contradiction— a Prieſt, as being of the Order of <hi>Loyola,</hi> and the Prophet of your own Afflictions—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                     <p>I wiſh I might have prov'd a falſe Prophet, tho' it had coſt me the ſpoiling of your Compliment, my Lord—But there's no ſtaying here—They are in quick purſuit I warr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ye, after us—therefore ſend for the Mayor and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>They attend without, Sir—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Mayor and Aldermen.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K. J.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen, I had a very good Army in <hi>England;</hi> but when I had the greateſt Occaſion for them, they deſerted me—When I came into this Kingdom, I found my <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects well equipped and prepared to defend my Cauſe. And tho' I had been often told, that when it came to the touch, they would never bear the brunt of a Battel, I would never believe it till now. 'Tis true, they did not deſert me as in <hi>England,</hi> yet
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53309:27"/>when it came to a Tryal, they baſely fled the Field, and left the Spoil to my Enemies—So that hence forward I never more deſire to head an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, and now am reſolv'd to ſhift for my ſelf; and ſo muſt you too. So, Gentleman, Farewell—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mayor.</speaker>
                     <p>Now is my Heart as heavy as a ſix Pounder—fit for nothing but a Grocer's Scales, to weigh Plums withal—and therefore to keep it from ſinking to the bottom of my Belly, I hope my Brethren and I ſhall endeavour to lighten it this Night, with your Majeſties Health before the Enemy comes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us—'Tis the laſt thing that we do for the depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſo may Heaven grant you ſucceſs with the ſame Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence, as we ſhall drink it with fidelity to your Cauſe—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>A pretty rough draught of Cordial Allegiance—yet ſomething better than Grief in one hand, and Sorrow in the other—Withal, my Lord Mayor—I muſt tell ye, that tho' it has been often debated, in Caſe a Revolution ſhould happen, whether upon deſerting of <hi>Dublin,</hi> the City ſhould not be fir'd, the King has conſider'd of it, and thinks it too Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous to be done—for tho' he affects the <hi>French</hi> Modes in all other things, in that he does not—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſee what a gracious Prince you were like to have had, and therefore let it be the laſt Act of your Obedience to repreſs all Inſolencies of the Rabble, and keep all things quiet, till your new Guardians come, and then let them alone—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mayor.</speaker>
                     <p>And I think too, the Proteſtants may be all let out of their Confinements, without any Orders of the Lieutenancy—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, Ay, my Lord, or elſe they'l let out themſelves—farewel, my Lord—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K. J.</speaker>
                     <p>Now, my Lords, let us poſt the next way to <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>—for I'me reſolv'd not to ſleep till I get a Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Herbert.</speaker>
                     <p>Pleaſe your Majeſty, I intend to bear you Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K. J.</speaker>
                     <p>With all my heart, my Lord—I always love to have Juſtice o' my ſide.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:53309:27"/>
                  <head>ACT. III. <hi>Scene</hi> 5.</head>
                  <stage>The Releaſed Proteſtants and Papiſts meet in the Streets, the Papiſts fawn upon 'em.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
                     <p>OH Neighbour, well met—I am heartily glad to ſee you at liberty again—By my ſhoule, Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, you cannot imagine how ſorry I was at your Confinement— By Creeſh, Neighbour, I did all that lay in my Power for you—went and ſpoke in your behalf; till I was ſo ſnubb'd for my pains, that I was forc'd to pull in my Horns, for fear of being taken for one of you—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, Neighbour, I heard what pains you took—and I thank you for it moſt heartily—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly Neighbour 'twas always my Opinion, that our Clergy were ſomewhat too ſevere—I wiſh they had been more mild, it might perhaps have been better for 'em—I told 'em of their Rigour many times—but then they were preſently Cock a Hoop—What are you a favourer of <hi>Hereticks?</hi>—and then my Mouth was preſently ſtopt—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, Neighbour, 'tis paſt now—and I pray God forgive 'em, for my part, I do—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Papiſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>O Neighbour, How I am overjoy'd at your delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance—I proteſt, Neighbour, I offer'd to be your Bail, and carryed another along with me, but it would not be taken—I think the Devil was in 'em to be ſo Cruel—I knew ye to be an Honeſt Man, and a juſt Dealer—and I would have paun'd all the Reputation I had in the World for ye, if they would have taken it—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
                     <p>I thank you kind Neighbour, I am very well ſatisfied in the Truth of what you ſay—and I wiſh they would have taken your ſecurity, for I was almoſt ſtifl'd, we were ſo crouded together—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Papiſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Neighbour! I proteſt I joy to ſee you out of your Trouble—did you never receive ſome inconſiderable trifling parcels of Money by a private hand—I know they were not worth ſpeaking of—but I'le aſſure you, upon the Word of a Chriſtian, 'twas I that ſent 'em—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le aſſure you, Neighbour, they were very acceptable—and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53309:28"/>I moſt cordially thank you for it—I knew Neighbour, 'twas your Charity, by the private mark you us'd to give your Money.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
                     <p>And did not at other times, the ſame private hand, bring you meat and drink?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, Neighbour, I muſt needs acknowledge it—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll aſſure ye 'twas I that ſent it—for I could not endure Men ſhould be ſo cruelly us'd—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
                     <p>I was not ignorant of your kindneſs, Neighbour—I knew the Meat by the dreſſing, and the Drink by the taſte— for I knew you had your meat always well dreſt, and kept good Drink in your Houſe—I hope I may live to retaliate your Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4. <hi>Papiſt.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Your moſt humble Servant, Mr. <hi>Clommell.</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
                     <p>I do not know you, Sir—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
                     <p>It may be ſo, Sir,—but were not you for two years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether moſt violently tormented with the Head-ach—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, Sir, I was ſo, but when King <hi>James</hi> was here, coming over <hi>Eſſex Bridge</hi> late i'th' Night, from viſiting ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Relations, ſome body or other, without the leaſt provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the World, gave me a cut o' the Head about ſeven Inches long, to my great eaſe as it prov'd, for the Pain has never troubl'd me ſince the Cure—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le aſſure ye, Sir, upon the word of a Chriſtian, 'twas I gave you that Cut—for by my skill in Surgery, I knew there was no other way to Cure ye—And I did it unexpectedly, for fear you would have been unwilling to have undergone the Cure, had you been told of it beforehand—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly Sir, 'twas a very great kindneſs, more than I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferv'd—and a very great Cure; and I'le aſſure ye, Sir, I ſhall recommend ye for a Curer of the Head-ach, to all I know that are in the ſame Condition that I then was—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt Papiſts—Proteſtants meet together.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Proteſtant.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Who lately thought of an Alteration like this, ſo ſudden and ſo Comfortable!—I could not reconcile my Bones to the hard Boards, for my life—they will hardly endure a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bed yet, they are ſo ſore—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Proteſtant.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>How did you find your Houſe at your return— I'm ſure they left me nothing but bare Walls—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Proteſtant.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Truly Neighbour, I have not heard a Mouſe ſtir in my Houſe yet—I believe they all went after our Proviſions to the Popiſh Habitations—and then for my Wares and Goods they are all vaniſhed—and yet I am ſure when I left 'em,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53309:28"/>they were all Corporeal Subſtances, that had they not been taken away, would never have mov'd of themſelves—Certainly Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage was very dear, during our Confinement—and I am apt to think they would have carry'd a way the very bare walls too, had they had time to pick down the Mortar.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Proteſtant.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Certainly ſince the <hi>Pariſian</hi> Maſſacre, never did Prince permit ſo much Barbariſm to be committed in the Metropolis of a Kingdom.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>5. <hi>Proteſtant.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>And yet now I cannot but ſmile—to hear our late Perſecutors and Slanderers tell us, what private friends they were to us in our neceſſities, to curry favour with us for fear of the ſame uſage—But for my part, I don't believe a tittle they ſay—only I give 'em cheap good words.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>6. <hi>Proteſtant.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>That it was debated whether they ſhould fire the City or no, in caſe they were forc'd to deſert it, is apparent by by the King's own confeſſion—and it was no leſs plain, that thoſe thoughts were laid aſide, more out of fear of the little Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to be expected from an Enemy ſo enrag'd—than out of any Kindneſs to us—and therefore now we are free, let us have a care of the ſame Yoke again—I hope we ſhall fight a little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for our Deliverer—than theſe Caterpillers did for their King—and ſo if you pleaſe, let us go and Drink the beſt Health in the World, To King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>ACT III. <hi>Scene</hi> 6.</head>
                  <stage>Tyrconnel, Lauzune, La Hoquette.</stage>
                  <p>I Saw him Shipt off—and I could not but let fall ſome of my Radical Moiſture at parting, but it was only like a ſhort <hi>April</hi> ſhower when the Sun ſhines—for indeed, under the Roſe be it ſpoken, our King is not the man I took him for—no man more impatient for the loſs of his Crown, no man more unwilling to venture himſelf for the recovery of it—</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzun.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, my Maſter's a <hi>Politician,</hi> and will not let him venture—He has charg'd him to the contrary—For if he be loſt, my Maſter loſes the chiefeſt Inſtrument he has to diſturb his moſt dreadful Adverſary.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>And when your Maſter finds he can do no good with him,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:53309:29"/>what will he do with him then?—For people have little Kindneſs for unfortunate Princes, eſpecially thoſe that ſhew themſelves more careful of their perſons, than of their Dominions. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if this laſt Act of his have not quite extinguiſhed that ſmall Remainder of Affection which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had for him, I think they are too blame, to be always venturing their Lives and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes in a leaky Bottom—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzune.</speaker>
                     <p>What will you do then, my Lord?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll e'en do as well as I can—I'le only ſtay to ſee <hi>Lymerick</hi> loſt,—and then I'le conſider—I muſt confeſs I have ſome Embers of gratitude ſtill glowing for my Old Patron and Raiſer,—and I would fain do as much for him as I could—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzune.</speaker>
                     <p>But what ſhall I do then, that have ſold all to ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Fortune of an Unfortunate Prince?—I am loth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn home to my own Country to be laught at—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith, my Lord, I would adviſe you to carry your <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gade</hi> into the <hi>Morea,</hi> as <hi>Hawksworth</hi> the Engliſh Taylor, in <hi>Ed.</hi> the thirds time, got leave to march into <hi>Italy,</hi> then variouſly in Arms, where he ſerv'd them that gave moſt, with that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, that at length he had the honour to be buried in <hi>Florence,</hi> under a noble Monument, by the name of <hi>Giovanni Acuto.</hi> My Lord, when you have got your Men into the <hi>Morea,</hi> you may either ſide with the <hi>Turk</hi> your Maſter's great Crony, or with the <hi>Venetian,</hi> which gives moſt; and by that means, after great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown acquir'd, you may chance to be buried either in St. <hi>Marks</hi> at <hi>Venice,</hi> or elſe in the Chief <hi>Moſquee</hi> in <hi>Conſtantinople</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzune.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhould be glad my Lord, of your Lordſhips Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and be willing you ſhould ſhare as well in my Fame, as in my Funerals—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Pardon me, my Lord, for being merry in misfortune—an ounce of Mirth is worth a pound of Sorow—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>But what ſhall I do then?—I have no Brigades to carry either to the <hi>Turk,</hi> or any where elſe—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzune.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! <hi>Lieutenant General,</hi> you may return again to your Native Country without Reflections—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>I think, my Lord, I have as much reaſon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain as you—our Maſter might have ſent ſome body elſe than us of his <hi>firſt</hi> of <hi>April</hi> Errands, into a Cowardly Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try—What Honour did he think we could win among a Company of Captain Cut-puddings that never intended to fight—Had we not underſtood the Right <hi>French</hi> way of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53309:29"/>fighting ſavingly, we had been all cut to pieces—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lords, I make no queſtion but you have both of ye made up your Mouths pretty well—This Iſland affords good ſtaple Commodities, that are good Chaffer in <hi>France</hi>—and ſure you did not burn ſo many Towns and Villages for nothing—certainly you skim'd off the Cream of the ſpoil for your ſelves—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hoquette.</speaker>
                     <p>Something <hi>begar</hi> we have got you may be ſure—but not ſo much as you think for, or we expected to gain—<hi>Ventre Goy,</hi> I was for plundering of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and then we might ha' fill'd both Pockets, Breeches and all—now we muſt be glad to get away with a Flea in our Ears, in Compariſon, as well as we can—Would I were well ſafe once, where ſome of my Luggage lyes—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzun.</speaker>
                     <p>I wiſh I were any where but where I am—here I neither Command, nor am Commanded—but lye ſtill for want of work, like a Brick-layer in Winter—<hi>Morbleu,</hi> I thought to have been Prince of <hi>Dublin</hi> before this—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                     <p>I queſtion, my Lord, whether that would have fallen to your ſhare—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzune.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mortbleu,</hi> had we beaten the Enemy, I could have beaten all your Men my ſelf—and then I would have try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed who was Maſter, your King or ours—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Ah, my Lord, I'me afraid you ſhew'd your Teeth too ſoon—and that was the reaſon our Dogs bit no clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Meſſenger.</stage>
                  <p>My Lords, the Engliſh Army is certainly marching towards ye in two Bodies—One General <hi>Douglas</hi> Commands, the other is headed by the Victorious Prince himſelf—</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzune.</speaker>
                     <p>We have been all along deluded with Stories and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths—Where are your fifty thouſand Men, my Lord, that were to riſe in <hi>England?</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, Sir, they are gone to joyn the twenty thouſand Men your Maſter ſent to take the I'le of <hi>Wight</hi>— don't your Lordſhip underſtand what belongs to falſe reports yet?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:53309:30"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzane.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes <hi>Begar,</hi> and to true ones too, my Lord—I wiſh I had never given Credit to the true ones, and I had never loſt my true Shouldier of Mutton, to ſnap at the ſhadow—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter ſecond Meſſenger.</stage>
                  <p>The Enemy comes on a-pace, and lyes this Night at <hi>Goolin Bridge</hi>—</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzune.</speaker>
                     <p>Were I not now in an Iſland, I could find a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred holes to creep out of this Labyrinth—I could joyn a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of my Maſter's Parties—But in this Lobs Pound, what the Diable ſhall I do with two thouſand five hundred Men—Well, my Lords, I'le leave <hi>Lymerick,</hi> for that would be to ſhut my ſelf up in a Pound, within a Pound, and retire to <hi>Gallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi>—There I ſhall either meet with Ships to carry off my Men—or elſe with new Reinforcements from my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <q>
                     <l>Was ever Man thus Bubbl'd <hi>Ventregoy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To ſell good Land to purchaſe a <hi>Decoy.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <head>ACT. III. <hi>Scene</hi> 7.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Meſſenger,</hi> Lauzune, Tyrconnel, Berwick, Hoquette, Sars<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, Talbot—</stage>
                  <p>MY Lords, I come with Winds and Sails as diligent to haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me, as I was zealous to bring you welcome Tidings from St. <hi>Germains.</hi>—</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Berwick.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou ſeem'ſt to have rather flown, than come by Sea—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>With the ſame ſpeed your Royal Father flew, who was at <hi>Tredah</hi> the Tenth of <hi>July,</hi> and the Twenty ſixth at St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Berwick.</speaker>
                     <p>And is my Royal Father well?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:53309:30"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Upon the twenty ſixth of <hi>July,</hi> your Royal Father arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at St. <hi>Germains,</hi> in the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Coaches, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed by the D. of <hi>Boüillon</hi>—Great Chamberlain; who was ſent to receive him in his Majeſty's Name—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                     <p>There's Honour ſtill, and Royal Reſpect I ſee, ſhewn even to my Father's Misfortunes—what would be done to his Proſperity!—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>The King went to viſit him the ſame day, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd him with all the Teſtimonies of a Tender and Ardent Affection—And made him new Proteſtations to ſupport him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Enemy, and to employ all his Forces to reſtore him; nor did he ſhew him any ſigns of being diſſatisfied with his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                     <p>There's new Conſolation for ye, my Lords, to raiſe your ſinking Spirits—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzune.</speaker>
                     <p>I wiſh they may come quickly, or elſe I fear I ſhall be in the Sudds, before their Arrival—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>[fetching a deep ſigh</hi>—</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                     <p>Why d'ye ſigh, my Lord?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzune.</speaker>
                     <stage>[Sighing again.]</stage>
                     <p>I know my Maſter's a great Diſſembler, my Lord, and I am well ſatisfied moreover, that he has other Fiſh to fry, than to employ all his Forces to aſſiſt your Royal Father—<hi>Morbleu,</hi> I don't like the beginning of the Story—Go on Meſſenger.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>The Viſit laſted above two Hours, and by the report of ſome that underſtand Affairs, 'twas not altogether ſpent in Complements—'Tis ſaid alſo, that your Royal Father is to go aboard the <hi>French</hi> Fleet, and endeavour to land in <hi>England,</hi> where he hopes to find a Conſiderable Party that will declare for him—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                     <p>I like this well—'Twas ſo order'd, to ſave my Father's Vow, who has determined never to head an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army more—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>The next Morning he went to <hi>Verſailles,</hi> to viſit her Majeſty, and return'd that Evening to the Queen his Royal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                     <p>And how did ſhe receive him?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <stage>[After a little ſtudying]</stage>
                     <p>Um—why—an't like your Grace, there were ſome little Bickerings between 'em at firſt—but the next Morning ſhe ſeem'd well contented.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:53309:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay—ſhe's a Woman never bears Malice long in her Mind—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>There's ſomething more that I have to ſay, but I'm loth to out with it —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                     <p>Out with it man—for fear of Choaking —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis ſaid—<hi>there ſtops</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee go on —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>—'Tis ſaid, that all the Welcomes and Careſſes which the King made your father, cannot reconcile him to the Eſteem of the Court Grandees—They ſay that <hi>William</hi> was truly born to Command, and <hi>James</hi> to obey—and that it was for your Father who had nothing more to loſe, to have acted the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of King <hi>William</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and for <hi>William</hi> the third to have ſpar'd himſelf, as your Royal Father did —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                     <p>And did they call him King <hi>William?</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, an't like your Grace—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le go and Challenge 'em every Mother's Son, as ſoon as I'me at leiſure—Well, but how does my Royal Father look, does he ſeem any way dejected?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Quite the contrary, Sir—He carries it with an Air and Countenance rather of a Prince Triumphant over his Enemies, than of a Perſon that had fled before 'em—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                     <p>Law ye now there, my Lords—You ſee my Royal Father's Heart whole ſtill—and the King of <hi>France</hi> ſticks to him— I find we ſhall have t'other Bruſh for't ſtill—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzune.</speaker>
                     <p>All this does not yet ſatisfie me—I'm ſure my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's too knowing in the Art of War, not to underſtand, that if his Arms have not proſper'd in <hi>Ireland,</hi> it muſt be in part the fault of him that commanded them—So that if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him kindly at his return, and appear'd ſatisfied with his Couduct, it was rather out of Policy, than from the bottom of his Heart—But my Maſter has ſtill need of him, to oppoſe the King of <hi>England,</hi> and therefore it is, that he is ſo good a Husband of him, and ſo behaves himſelf towards him as if he were the greateſt General in the World—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsfield.</speaker>
                     <p>You are ſo full of Scruples, my Lord—you ſuppoſe and believe, and believe and ſuppoſe this and that and t'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther— I believe and ſuppoſe no ſuch thing—I believe the King of <hi>France</hi> to be real, and that he ſeriouſly intends to do as he ſays—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:53309:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Otherwiſe he were the moſt ungrateful Perſon in the World—for when it lay in our Maſter's Power he did all that he could for him—Nay, I may boldly ſay, that had it not been for our Maſter, he had never come to what he is—I will inſtance yee only in one thing, and that was in mannaging all the Dutch Wars for your Maſter's ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tal.</speaker>
                     <p>Gad I believe the moſt Chriſtian King to be one of the Honeſteſt Gentlemen in <hi>Europe</hi>—and my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe he always lov'd a handſom Girl—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                     <p>Look yee, my Lords, you muſt grant me that Kings Heads are better than other Mens Heads—And if ſo, then two Kings Heads are better than one—ſo that I am confident, after theſe two Kings have laid their Heads toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a little while, you'll ſee ſtrange Alterations in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tal.</speaker>
                     <p>Wou'd he were hang'd that does not not believe your Grace ſpeaks like an Angel—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sarsfield.</speaker>
                     <p>For my part, I hope to be revelling in <hi>London</hi>— Let me ſee—How long firſt?—do you appoint a time, my Lord—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tyrcon.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly, my Lord, I can't—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sars.</speaker>
                     <p>Before—before—<hi>Tueſday</hi> come Sennight—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzune.</speaker>
                     <p>—Not ſo ſoon, Colonel—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sars.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le hold ye, my Lord, a hundred Guineys to one on't.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lauzune.</speaker>
                     <p>Wagers are Fools Arguments, Colonel—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sars.</speaker>
                     <p>By the Bones of my Father, I'le take the Lye from ne'er a <hi>French</hi> Bougre—Diable of ye all—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Draws—They all draw, take Parties, fall a fighting, and ſo put an end to the laſt Act.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:53309:32"/>
            <head>Epilogue.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I <hi>Wonder what our Audience will ſay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of this our Thundring, drumming, fighting Play?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here are no Scenes indeed, as will invite,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We bring 'em or, but yet they will not fight.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Theſe</hi> Iriſh <hi>are of juſt the ſelf ſame Kidney,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Like the two Cowards in Sir</hi> Philip Sidny.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They Huff, preſent, Rage, foam, look big and Swear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But ſomething whiſpers to 'em,</hi> have a Care.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such Sparks the Ladies Hatred cannot lack,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They hate the Man, that always turns his Back:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>No, they by other methods muſt be won,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They like the Man that briskly puſhes on.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis ſtrange what Nature made theſe Iriſh for,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They're neither good in Peace, nor fit for War;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The higheſt Office they are fit for moſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is to be Trotters in the Penny Poſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh! were they all upon a Famous Plain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Where never yet was daring Monarch ſlain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From whence, to</hi> Rome, <hi>if we could them Convey,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We gladly would the charge of Carriage pay.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:53309:32"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE <hi>Folly</hi> of <hi>Prieſt Craft,</hi> a Comedy.</p>
            <p>To the two Univerſities, an Epiſtle; together with a Prediction, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>French,</hi> Tranſlated out of <hi>Callimachus,</hi> who is by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaid to be a Prophet, and that his Teſtimony is true. <hi>Titus Ch.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 12. 13.</p>
            <p>The Addreſs given in to the late King <hi>James,</hi> by the titular Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Dublin,</hi> from the general Meeting of the Romiſh Biſhops and Clergy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> held in <hi>May</hi> laſt, by that King's Order; wherein ſeveral things relating to the Popiſh Deſigns upon theſe three Kingdoms, are diſcovered, the Original whereof was found in the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Cloſet, in the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> at his leaving that City: And the Copy whereof was found in the titular Arch-Biſhop's Lodgings. Now pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed with Reflections on each Paragraph.</p>
            <p>A True Relation of the Cruelties and Barbarities of the <hi>French,</hi> upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſoners of War. Being a Journal of their Travels from <hi>Dinan</hi> in <hi>Britany,</hi> to <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> in <hi>Provence;</hi> and back again. With a Deſcription of the Scituation, and Fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of all the Eminent Towns upon the Road, and their Diſtance. Of their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Hoſpitals, and the Number of Men that died under their Cruelty: With the Names of many of them, and the places of their Deaths and Burials: With an Account of the great Charity and ſufferings of the poor Proteſtants of <hi>France;</hi> And other material Things that happened upon the Way.</p>
            <p>The Memoirs of Monſiour <hi>Deageant;</hi> containing the moſt ſecret Tranſactions and Affairs, from the Death of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. till the beginning of the Miniſtry of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>de Richlieu.</hi> To which is added, a particular Relation of the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Embrun</hi>'s Voyage into <hi>England,</hi> and of his Negotiation for the Advancement of the Roman-Catholick Religion here; together with the Duke of <hi>Buckingham's</hi> Letters to the ſaid Arch-Biſhop, about the Progreſs of that Affair; which happen'd the laſt Years of King <hi>James</hi> l, his Reign. Faithfully tranſlated out of the <hi>French</hi> Original.</p>
            <p>The Cabinet Open'd; or, the Secret Hiſtory of the Amours of Madam <hi>de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenon</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> King. Tranſlated from the <hi>French</hi> Copy.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the moſt Illuſtrious <hi>William</hi> P. of <hi>Orange;</hi> Deduc'd from the firſt Founders of the Ancient Houſe of <hi>Naſſau;</hi> together with the moſt conſiderable Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this preſent Prince. The ſecond Edition.</p>
            <p>A Collection of Fourteen Papers, relating to the Affairs of Church and State, in the Reign of the late King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Character of a Trimmer. His Opinion of, I. The Laws and Government. II. The Proteſtant Religion. III. The Papiſts. IV. Foreign Affairs. By the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. Sir <hi>William Coventry.</hi> The third Edition, carefully Corrected, and cleared from the Errors of the firſt Impreſſion.</p>
            <p>An Impartial Relation of the Illegal Proceedings againſt St. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in <hi>Oxon,</hi> in the Year of our Lord 1687. Containing only Matters of Fact as they occurred. The Second Edition. To which is added the moſt remarkable Paſſages o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the former. Collected by a Fellow of the ſaid Colledge.</p>
            <p>The Juſtice of the Parliament, in inflicting of Puniſhments ſubſequent to Offenders' vindicated; and the lawfulneſs of the preſent Government aſſerted.</p>
            <p>An Account of Mr. <hi>Perkinſon</hi>'s Expulſion from the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> in late times in vindication of him from the falſe Aſperſions caſt upon him, in a late Pamphlet, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>The Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Way to Peace among all Proteſtants; being a Letter of Reconcillation, ſent by Bp. <hi>Ridley,</hi> to Bp. <hi>Hooper.</hi> By Mr. <hi>Sam. Johnſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Purgatory prov'd by Miracles; collected out of <hi>Roman-Catholick</hi> Authors. With ſome remarkable Hiſtories relating to <hi>Britiſh, Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Saints, with a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face concerning their Miracles. By Mr. <hi>Sam. Johnſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53309:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Seaſonable Diſcourſe, ſhewing the unreaſonableneſs and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs of Impoſition in Matters of Religion; Recommended, to a ſerious Conſideration. By Mr. <hi>Andrew Marvel,</hi> late Member of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Revolter.</hi> A Tragi-Comedy, acted between the <hi>Hind</hi> and <hi>Panther,</hi> and <hi>Religio Laici.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Collection of Poems, Satyrs, and Songs, againſt Popery and Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. In four Parts. Moſt of them writ by the late Duke of <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Andrew Marvel,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Aylof,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stephen Colledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Anſwer to the Bp. of <hi>Rocheſter</hi>'s firſt and ſecond Letters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Intrigues of the <hi>French</hi> King at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to imbroll <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> diſcover'd in ſeveral Diſpatches paſt between him and the late Grand Signior, Grand Vizier, and Count <hi>Teckely;</hi> all of them ſound among that Count's Papers. With ſome Reflections upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The New Nonconformiſt.</hi> Or, Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Caſe in preaching af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Deprivation, incurr'd by the Expreſs words of a Statute; fairly Stated and examined. With ſome ſhort Reflections upon Mr. <hi>Cook</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>Feb.</hi> 2. 1690. which was Licens'd by the Arch-Biſhop's Chaplain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Fate of France.</hi> A Diſcourſe where it is ſhew'd, That by the <hi>Happy Revolution</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> all the Deſigns of the <hi>French</hi> King for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy</hi> are diſappoined; and the Rational Grounds to believe his Downfal near. In three Dialogues betwixt Father <hi>Petre,</hi> Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> and two <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Gentlemen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Anatomy of a Jacobite Tory.</hi> In a Dialogue between <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Tory,</hi> occaſioned by the Act for Recognizing K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Great Baſtard, Protector of the Little One.</hi> Done out of <hi>French.</hi> And for which the <hi>French</hi> King put forth a <hi>Proclamation,</hi> with a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of five thouſand <hi>Louis d'Ors</hi> to diſcover the Author.</p>
            <p>Reflections upon a Form of Prayer, lately ſet forth by the <hi>Jacobites</hi> of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and of an Abhorrence, tendred by the late King to ſome of our Diſſenting Biſhops, upon his preſent Majeſties Landing.</p>
            <p>A true Account of a late horrid Couſpiracy to betray <hi>Holland</hi> to the <hi>French</hi> And of the Tryal, Confeſſion, Condemnation and Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Jacob Martinet,</hi> Sheriff of the Town of <hi>Sluys;</hi> and <hi>Cornelius Reoland,</hi> Maſter of the Ship call'd the <hi>Argle</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> who were Executed for the ſaid Conſpiracy, <hi>May</hi> 6. 1690.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſſex</hi>'s Innocency and Honour vindicated; Or <hi>Murther, Subornation, Perjury</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> juſtly charg'd on the Murderers of that Noble Lord, and True Patriot, <hi>Arthur</hi> (late) Earl of <hi>Eſſex.</hi> As prov'd before the Right Honourable (late) Committee of Lords, <hi>are ready to be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. By</hi> Laurnece Braddon, <hi>Gent.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
